<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The complaint of England Wherein it is clearely prooued that the practises of traitrous papists against the state of this realme, and the person of her Maiestie, are in diuinitie vnlawfull, odious in nature, and ridiculous in pollicie. In the which they are reprooued of wilfull blindnes, in that they see not the filthines of the Romish gouernment: and conuinced of desperate madnesse, in that they feare not the mischiefe of Spanish inuasion: the former whereof is exemplified by the Popes practises both here in England, and abroad in other countries: the later by the Spaniards outrages, in his exactions raised vpon Naples, and his tyrannies executed in the Indies. Lastly the necessitie, equitie, and benefits of the late proceeding in iustice are set downe; with a friendly warning to seditious papists for their amendment; and an effectuall consolation to faithfull subiectes for their incouragement. Seene and allowed.</title>
            <author>[Lightfoot, William].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108556</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844214</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844214</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9005</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05463)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9005)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 263:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The complaint of England Wherein it is clearely prooued that the practises of traitrous papists against the state of this realme, and the person of her Maiestie, are in diuinitie vnlawfull, odious in nature, and ridiculous in pollicie. In the which they are reprooued of wilfull blindnes, in that they see not the filthines of the Romish gouernment: and conuinced of desperate madnesse, in that they feare not the mischiefe of Spanish inuasion: the former whereof is exemplified by the Popes practises both here in England, and abroad in other countries: the later by the Spaniards outrages, in his exactions raised vpon Naples, and his tyrannies executed in the Indies. Lastly the necessitie, equitie, and benefits of the late proceeding in iustice are set downe; with a friendly warning to seditious papists for their amendment; and an effectuall consolation to faithfull subiectes for their incouragement. Seene and allowed.</title>
                  <author>[Lightfoot, William].</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[68] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, dwelling in Distaffe lane, neere the signe of the Castle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1587.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: William Lightfoote.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴ I² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9005:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9005:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Complaint <hi>of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein it is clearely prooued that the practiſes of Traitrous Papiſts againſt the ſtate of this Realme, and the perſon of her Maieſtie, are in Diuinitie vnlawfull, odious in Nature, and ridiculous in pollicie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the which they are reprooued of wilfull blindnes, in that they ſee not the filthines of the Romiſh gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and conuinced of deſperate madneſſe, in that they feare not the miſchiefe of Spaniſh inuaſion: The former whereof is exemplified by the Popes practiſes both here in England, and abroad in other countries: the later by the Spaniards outrages, in his exactions raiſed vpon</hi> Naples, <hi>and his tyrannies executed in the</hi> Indies.</p>
            <p>Laſtly the neceſsitie, equitie, and benefits of the late proceeding in iuſtice are ſet downe; with a friendly warning to ſeditious Papiſts for their amendment; and an effectuall conſolation to faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubiectes for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fata viam inuenient, aderit<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vocatus Apollo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seene and allowed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by Iohn Wolfe, dwelling in Diſtaffe lane, neere the ſigne of the Caſtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1587.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:9005:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Sic ſibi <hi>Walworthus</hi> caeſo latrone perenne</l>
               <l>ſic vrbi peperit Londigeníſque decus.</l>
               <l>Londigena infeſtum patriae qui nutriet hoſtem</l>
               <l>Londigenis pariet dedecus atque ſibi.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9005:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE SIR <hi>George Barne Knight, Lord Maior of the</hi> Citie of London; and the right worſhipfull the <hi>Aldermen his Brethren and aſsiſtants,</hi> peace and ioie in Chriſt Ieſus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an <hi>axiome</hi> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in philoſophie, and a truth apparant in dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie experience, that ſmall forces firmly vnited and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pacted in one, grow to bee mightie in continuance of time: whereas matters of far greater moment being ſeparated either by caſuall diuiſion, or wilfull diſcord, are eaſily ruinated, and ſodainly brought to confuſion. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Nature in all her actions intending <hi>vnitie,</hi> buildeth her whole frame vpon the groundworke of ſweete harmonie, and muſicall concent: tempering the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in each ſeuerall body with ſuch indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent
<pb facs="tcp:9005:3"/>proportion, that albeit ſome one ouerrule the reſt, yet it is not permitted to ouerthrow them: but they all by a ſecret <hi>ſympathie</hi> &amp; mutual agreement, indeuour to ſupport the one the others burden. But whenſoeuer this <hi>vniſone</hi> is interrupted by iarring of the parts, then is Nature by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence rackt out of her courſe, and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on inſueth the ſubuerſion of the whole. Seeing then <hi>vnitie</hi> is the marke whereat Nature aimeth, and the verie meane to preſerue her woorkes: and ſeeing ſuch thinges of all others doe chiefly promiſe perpetuitie, as draw neereſt to the rule of Nature; it is an vndoubted conſequent that thoſe common wealthes haue grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt likelihood of proſperitie, &amp; leaſt cauſe of decaie, wherein concord is nouriſhed, and diſſenſion ſuppreſſed. Mitigation of puniſhment is a dangerous imboldening of malicious aduerſaries; and obſtinate purpoſes, vnles they be timely preuented by politike foreſight, and reſtrained by ſpeciall penaltie, are often times too late
<pb facs="tcp:9005:3"/>repented, when in the end they burſt out into vnlawfull practiſes, to the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of publike <hi>vnitie</hi> and the procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of common confuſion. Therefore as the maintenance of <hi>vnitie</hi> is an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that conſerueth the ſtate: ſo is exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of iuſtice the golden piller that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth <hi>vnitie.</hi> The which prop ſo long as it ſhall ſtand in force (but it muſt ſtand in force ſo long as <hi>England</hi> will deſire to reſt in ſafetie) I hope the Traitrous intents of <hi>Englands</hi> and Engliſh enemies ſhall be vtterly fruſtrate, neither ſhall they haue ſo great cauſe to triumph for their victories, as ſhe hath now iuſt reaſon to complaine of their trecheries. For by the cutting off, of putrified members the whole bodie maie be deliuered from perill: and by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoiding odious iarres, amiable <hi>vnitie</hi> may be retained. But if their hidden rancour be ſuffered inwardly to feſter, and further to diſperſe it ſelfe, then it is greatly to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red leaſt the contagion thereof breede a fouler maladie, then can bee cured with
<pb facs="tcp:9005:4"/>an ordinarie plaiſter. In reſpect whereof your honors &amp; worſhips trauailes ioint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſeuerally imploied in theſe dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous times, as they argue a ſtudious zeale and affectionate deuotion towards your naturall Prince and countrie: ſo doe they merit all titles of ſingular commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. The renowne of diuers your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors is with capitall letters ſo inregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the booke of <hi>Fame,</hi> that neither the darkeſome vaile of <hi>Obliuion</hi> can ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadow it, nor the forked ſting of <hi>detrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> at anie time cancell it. In imitation of whoſe worthines if yee ſhall conſtantly proceede, as ye haue alreadie laudably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, it will appeere that vertue yet ſtoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not for age, and that common care is not brought a ſleepe by priuate profit. This argument might miniſter ample matter of true diſcourſe: but leaſt my words ſhould be wreſted beyond the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell of my thoughts, &amp; ſo attainted with ſuſpicion of flatterie, I wrap that vp in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence which I might very wel vtter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:9005:4"/>anie impeachment of inſinuation; omitting your induſtrious care for ſifting out recuſants, your diligent ſearch for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery of factions, your watchfull regard for appeaſing of mutinies, your charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prouiſion for relieuing of Orphanes, with diuers other matters of importance greatlie behoofefull to the ſtate of this Realme, &amp; properly incident to the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of good Magiſtrates. And ſeeing theſe are the daies wherein treaſon is coloured with religion &amp; malice armed with poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, I haue in this treatiſe detected the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of Traitors, and vſed diſſuaſions by manifeſting the dangers annexed to their proceedings. The which for that it is fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the perſon of <hi>England</hi> whome yee haue oft aſsiſted in extremities, I haue publiſhed vnder your L. and W. patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and offer the ſame to your accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, whom th'almightie protect with his power, and guide with his grace.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your L. and VV. at commaund,</hi> William Lightfoote.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:9005:5"/>
            <head>Ad pontificios Apoſtrophe.</head>
            <l>PApicola ergo fremis, triplicis quòd pompa tiarae</l>
            <l>ſordet, &amp; in nihilum perdita Roma ruit?</l>
            <l>Papa quòd est vulgò papae; quòd Roma, ruina;</l>
            <l>miſſa quòd eſt monstrum; papicola ergo fremis?</l>
            <l>Vah freme; frendat aper, furiat rabioſa caterua:</l>
            <l>euomat in proprium toxica dir a ſinum.</l>
            <l>Accingis lateri gladios, vibraſque ſagittas,</l>
            <l>confodit ast pectus tortilis hasta tuum.</l>
            <l>In fumos abeunt cerebri deliria laeſi,</l>
            <l>machina quam fabricas mole ſuapte ruit.</l>
            <l>Nos ridere minas; nos flocci pendere pugnas;</l>
            <l>nos tremere ad belli fulmina falſa nihil.</l>
            <l>Paſtor oues curat, ſic curat Chriſtus ouile,</l>
            <l>praedantemque fugat peruigil ipſe lupum.</l>
            <l>Et nos ſub Chriſti placidè requieſcimus vmbra:</l>
            <l>hem tibi: te faſces, virga, cruceſque manent.</l>
            <l>Dum ſimulas Petrum, in petram comping is ineptè:</l>
            <l>inde luent ſcapulae; papicola ergo geme.</l>
            <l>Dum ſtimulum calcas, intentat Alecto flagellum,</l>
            <l>imminet in poenam vindice dura manu.</l>
            <l>Inſultas tumidus quaſi victima pinguis in aras,</l>
            <l>neſcius (o) fati; papicola ergo geme.</l>
            <l>Pro fremitu gemitus ſubeat, cedatque dolori</l>
            <l>iam dolus, &amp; curae ſit tibi ſola ſalus.</l>
            <l>Reginam &amp; patriam miſeris iactare procellis</l>
            <l>impius optâſti; papicola ergo geme.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Guil. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9005:5"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Complaint of England.</head>
            <head type="sub">England ſpeaketh.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſorrowes which I haue lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp within the cloſet of my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed thoughts, ſpringing from the infected puddle of thoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall and miſchieuous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes, that haue bene lately practiſed for the working of my ruine, by vndermining of my ſtate, are now grown to ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie of paſſion, that they, in a maner, bereaue my ſoule of comfort, and debarre my ſpeeche of paſſage. And although I haue ſmall hope by my perſwaſions to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine them from trecherous and deſperate enterpriſes,
<note place="margin">Small hope to preuaile by wordes when deedes take no place.</note> whome by my benefftes I cannot allure to continue in loyall obedience: (who hauing their iudgement blinded with ambitious deſire of promotion; their heartes ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately grounded on wilfull opinion of error; theyr mindes dangerouſly inuenomed with the poiſon of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueterate malice: haue (I feare me) baniſhed all feare of God, quenched eache ſparke of religion, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced all reſpect of allegeaunce) yet it may be that if I ſhall by manifeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and infallible demonſtration proue, that the inſtruments they haue deuiſed for mine ouerthrow, will in concluſion redound to their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: and the weapons they daily forge to gore my ſides withall, muſt needes in the end cut theyr owne throates, and be ſheathed in theyr proper intrailes:
<pb facs="tcp:9005:6"/>then (I ſay) it is poſſible that the regard of theyr owne ſafetie,
<note place="margin">Doubt of danger a bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle for a brain ſicke Iade.</note> may be verie forcible to ſtirre vp in them ſome relenting motions, though the head-ſtrong fury of their reſolution will not giue them leaue to conſider the hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſſe of theyr purpoſe, nor to harken to the iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my complaint. At the leaſt I am aſſured of this, that howe ſoeuer they haue by villanous dowes ſold themſelues to be veſſels and vaſſalles of iniquitie, howe ſoeuer they haue receiued the ſtampe of the beaſt in theyr forehead, howe ſoeuer they haue taken afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand the earneſt penny of theyr graund captayne Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than to accompliſhe his commaund: yet this I knowe, that the Almightie, who from the higheſt heauens looketh with ſingle eye into the bottome and moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret corners of theyr double heartes, will in the zeale of hys iuſtice award them a wrathfull and irreuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſentence of indgement, from the which they ſhall not appeale, repaying vengeaunce for theyr hire; and will in the fulneſſe of hys compaſſion beholde myna innocencie, makyng heauen and earthe to wonder at theyr madneſſe, the world to witneſſe theyr outrages, and theyr owne conuicted conſciences to teſtifie howe vndeſeruedly they haue vndertaken agaynſt me, the execution of ſuch monſtrous and mercileſſe intentions. How can I but bluſhe to call them ſonnes, who viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſacred laws of nature, haue ſought to prefer an vniuſt ſtepdame before their moſt louing mother?
<note place="margin">They that chaunge the libertie of the Goſpell for popiſh thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, muſt needes liue by the loſſe, and purchaſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance at too deare a rate.</note> How can I but ſorrow at their ſenſeleſſe and ouer growne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, who reiecting the ſweet yoke of dutifull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection, preſume to lift vp theyr heele agaynſt her head, vnder whoſe feete they ought to laie downe their liues? And needes muſt I condemne their abiect and caitife courage, who being free borne and enioying abſolute li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, are notwithſtanding ſo bewitched with ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, that going about vnder a friuolous pretence of purchaſing greater freedome (forſooth) to theyr conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,
<pb facs="tcp:9005:6"/>they are contented to abandon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall flauerie to ſuch tyrannie, as doth not onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtome it ſelfe to make hauocke of ſubſtance and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions; to exerciſe butcherlie maſſacres on the bodie; but it alſo ouer chargeth the ſoule with clogges of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall bondage, which being once taken are intollerable to beare, and almoſt impoſſible to ſhake off.</p>
            <p>Come neare me yet my ſonnes, my diſobedient ſounes: (woe is me that the inſtinct of nature infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth me to call you ſonnes, who haue ſo muche dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated in your vngratious behauiours, that you ſhame and ſcorne to acknowledge me for your mother) come neare me (I ſay) ſequeſter not your ſelues from my preſence, but tell me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what ground this ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ariſeth. If from feare; (which I hardly beleeue) know that I which incloſed you in my bowels, nurſed you at my breſts, imbraced you in mine arms, and carry you ſtil ingrauen on the table of my heart, haue not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten the affection of a mother, but am willing to grant you pardon for your faults, if you can finde grace to be ſorie for the ſame: and therefore be not afraid. If from ſhame; (which I heartily wiſh) then ſhall I thinke that this is the firſt ſtep to your amendment, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I perceiue you abaſht at the conceit of your former lewdnes; and then ſhall I hope you will take a newe courſe, when I ſee you breake off from your olde bias. It is no ſhame to be aſhamed of euill doing: it is neuer too late to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme bad conditions. The medicine commeth not out of time that bringeth remedie when it is miniſtred: and therefore ſet ſhame aſide. If from ſelfe-loue or malice;
<note place="margin">Truth muſt needes haue a colde ſuite where malice is chiefe Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iudge.</note> (whiche by coniectures more then probable I am induced deepelie to ſuſpect) remember that ſelfo loue is partiall, and bolteth out hys verdict before hee haue throughlie examined the cauſe: knowe that malice is blinde, and lyeth alwayes in the heauier ballance, making equitie to ſeeme light waight: and
<pb facs="tcp:9005:7"/>therfore awaie with ſuch companions. So then whence ſoeuer this ſtrangeneſſe ariſeth, draw neare notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and let vs a while reaſon togither. I will not aſſume the title of my iuſt authoritie: I will not challenge the priuiledge of a mother: neither will I greatly vrge you with the duetie of Children: but we will deale indifferently, and ſo where the fault is iuſtly found, there ſhall the blame worthily remaine.</p>
            <p>Say on then; what ſufficient reaſons, or what iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſurmiſes feede this diſcontented humour in you? Why ſpeake you not? what argueth this ſtlence? this guiltie ſilence? May it ſound credible in any impartiall eares, that you haue with ſuch rigorous cenſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned me, with ſuch vnſlakt thirſt of reuenge perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted me, againſt whome you cannot alleadge anie co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable accuſation? Anſwere me, and ſo diſburde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your conſciences; or elſe bethinke you what aunſwere you wil then frame, when you ſhalbe ſummoned to appeare before the ſupreme tribunal in the higheſt court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement; where you cannot pleade by proxie, nor enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain your attourney; where al popiſh diſpenſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhall be fruſtrate; where no conſtruction of aduantage wil be admitted; where deuiſed cauils ſhalbe excluded; where God himſelf ſhalbe plaintife, aduocate, and iudge, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence action, to beare witnes, &amp; to pronounce ſentence againſt you. If I had conſumed your wealth by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of <hi>Naples,</hi> if I had diſturbed your quiet by the Inquiſition of <hi>Seuill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neither pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate wrong nor publicke wracke can ſerue to bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter out tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes.</note> if I had tyrannized your liues by Spaniſh cruelties, or inthralled your ſoules to Romiſh ſuperſtition, then might you haue ſhaped out ſome ſhadow of reaſon, &amp; pretended argument of probability, for the oppoſing of your ſelues, and the depoſing of her, who had ſought to forment you with ſuch helliſh miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: yet were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> too too weak, for to build either open rebellion,
<note place="margin">Pſalme, 10 5.</note> or ſecret conſpiracy therupon. Are ye not expreſly forbidden to touch the Lords annointed? and
<pb facs="tcp:9005:7"/>can it then be warranted vnto you, to lay violent hands and griping pawes vpon her? I warrant you it is a leaden warrant for the baſenes, and braſen for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencie; trie it when you liſt at the touchſtone, you ſhall finde it not currant, but counterfeite; and they will in fine proue them ſelues Calues, that hope to ſucke anie comforte or confidence out of ſuch a Bull.</p>
            <p>Know ye not that he who dwelleth in heauen,
<note place="margin">Pſalme. 2.</note> laugheth them to ſcorne that furiouſly rage, or ſo much as take counſell together againſt him and his annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? and annexeth to his deriſion burning wrath and ſore diſpleaſure, bruiſing them with a rod of yron, and breaking them in péeces like a potters veſſel? Suppoſe ye that the quarrel of the Lords annointed concerneth him not, or toucheth him not to the verie quicke? will not he, thinke ye, redreſſe the wrong, and take the cauſe into his owne handes? haue ye liued ſo long, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſo litle? or doe ye know this perfectly, and yet prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe the contrarie purpoſely? O blind as Béetles, if ye ſée not this: O faithles as Atheiſts, if ye belieue not this? O fooliſh as Idiots, if ye beware it not: Would it not be accounted, I will not ſay a point of ridiculous follie, but an euident proofe of extréeme madneſſe in the higheſt degrée, if a ſéely perſon enféebled by long ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhould in the beldem rage and franticke bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his maladie preſume to encounter a valiant champion, and to wreſt the weapon out of his handes? And can it in common eſtimation be thought leſſe then deteſtable impietie, that men long languiſhing in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of reaſon, but abounding with a contagious humor of innouation, forlorn in hope, fallen from grace, and reprobate in ſenſe, ſhall in the fit &amp; agonie of their brainſicke diſeaſe, reare vp ladders to ſcale the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, combining them ſelues by force to ſeaze vpon the awfull ſcepter, and with tooth and naile to bite and ſcratch after the crowne on their Princes head? What
<pb facs="tcp:9005:8"/>is it to wage battaile,
<note place="margin">They that reſiſt a lawful Prince make war againſt the liuing God.</note> and maintaine wars with God, if this be not? This is to verifie the fable of the giants, who are ſaide to haue rampired bulwarkes, and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their engins, threatning to diſlodge <hi>Iupiter</hi> of his throne.</p>
            <p>It is manifeſt that <hi>Dauid</hi> the choſen ſeruant of God,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 24.</note> notwithſtanding that <hi>Saule</hi> cauſeleſſe purſued him, and like an enraged Tigre gréedily haſting after his pray, ſo hunted after his ſoule: yet at ſuch time as <hi>Saule</hi> at vnwares entred into the caue where <hi>Dauid</hi> with his ſeruants were couertly hidden, albeit <hi>Dauid</hi> was by his men of war animated, and by inceſſant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie vrged to laie hold vpon preſent occaſion, and ſo to preuent future peril, who in moſt veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t maner inforced their purpoſe, ſaying: <hi>See, the daie is come whereof the Lord ſaid vnto thee, Behold I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer thine enimie into thine hand, and thou ſhalt doe with him as it ſhall ſeeme good to thee:</hi>
               <note place="margin">This exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Dauid</hi> ought to be throughlie waighed and trueite fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</note> yet, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ruthfull conſideration of his perplexed eſtate, nor the peremptorie threats of his ſworne enimie, nor the effectuall obteſtations of his approued ſouldiours could any iote preuaile with him for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an action ſo hainous and accurſed. But he was touched in his hart, becauſe he had touched and cut off the lap of his Lords garment. And thereupon diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelfe, hee inclined his face to the earth, and bowed himſelfe before <hi>Saule,</hi> manifeſſing his innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. <hi>Saule</hi> aſtoniſhed at the matter, and déepely raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with the contemplation of ſuch vndeſerued fauor, and inexpected curteſie, lift vp his voice and wept, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto <hi>
                  <hi>Dauid:</hi> Thou art more righteous then I: for I haue wrought thee euil, and thou haſt rendered me good: for who ſhall find his enimie, and let him depart free?</hi> And afterwarde (as appeareth in theſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel of the hiſtorie) when <hi>Saules</hi> power fighting againſt the Philiſtines, was diſcomfited, and himſelfe deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:9005:8"/>of victorie, and wearie of life, fell vpon the point of his ſword: at ſuch time as a young man of the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekites,</hi> thinking to deliuer an acceptable meſſage, and hoping he ſhould haue reaped a gladſome welcome for reporting ſuch ioyfull tidings, tolde vnto <hi>Dauid</hi> that he at the intreatie and inſtant requeſt of <hi>Saule,</hi> had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatched him of his life, the enioying whereof was irkeſome and full of anguiſh vnto him: and more, leſt he ſhould haue omitted anie thing, that hee thought might gratifie <hi>Dauid,</hi> or worke his ſinguler content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he preſented him with the crowne that he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from <hi>Saules</hi> head, thereby both confirming the truth of his ſpéeches, and alſo (after a ſort) inſtalling <hi>Dauid</hi> in poſſeſſion of the ſame: yet was he ſo farre from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing, either in that his aduerſaries death had finiſhed his troubles, and aſſured him of his life with ſecuritie, or that none other could foreſtall him in obtaining the kingdom, that he rent his clothes, wept &amp; faſted vntill e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening, and then ſaid to the meſſenger:
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 1.</note> 
               <hi>How waſt thou not affraid to put forth thine hand to deſtroie the annointed of the Lord? Thy bloud be vpon thine owne head; for thine owne mouth hath teſtified a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee.</hi> And therewith commanded one of his ſeruants to fall vpon him, who ſmote him that hee dyed.</p>
            <p>This one example, if the volume of Gods booke, (which is the teſtament of his trueth, and the ſtorehouſe of his promiſes) did not afforde any greater plentie, might alone ſuffice, for the deciding of a queſtion ſo néedleſſe, and ſo vngodlie. This alone might ſerue for the ſuppreſſing of ſuch hatefull conſpiracies, as the graceleſſe broodes of mongrell monſters (I meane En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Italianates) doe ingender and hatch within their diueliſh conceites. This, yea this being authentike, vndoubted, and entangled with no ſcruple, might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſerue for a moſt exquiſite preſident, whereto ye
<pb facs="tcp:9005:9"/>ought to conforme your thoughtes, and whereby ye ought to confirme that reuerend opinion, which all men are to carrie of lawfull Princes being Gods deputies. In the which ſithence there are diuers occurrents well worthie the obſeruation, it will not be impertinent ſlightly to glaunce at, and briefly to compriſe the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances and differences, which ſhew themſelues in this fact of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and this faction of yours: that for ſo much as the nature of contraries is beſt tryed by matching and comparing the one with the other: therefore by how much the fact of <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhall appeare more iuſt and righteous, by ſo much will your faction be proued more odious and damnable. <hi>Saule,</hi> becauſe he diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the commandement of the Lorde vttered by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Samuel,</hi> was forſaken of God: Gods holy ſpirite departed from him, and an euil ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite tooke poſſeſſion of him: <hi>Dauid</hi> was by <hi>Samuel</hi> annointed king in his ſteade. Yet would he not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to diſpoſſeſſe <hi>Saule</hi> of his kingdom: but endured grieuous calamities which by the malice of <hi>Saule</hi> were inflicted vpon him. He was diſtreſſed in the townes with doubt of trecheries; vexed in the wilderneſſe with the ſcourge of penurie; reproched by the churle <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> with the infamous title of runnagate; conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in king <hi>Achis</hi> Court to counterfeit madneſſe; ſuſtaining a burthen of miſeries heauier then <hi>Aetna,</hi> and almoſt ouerwhelmed with an Ocean of perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Yet did hée with all méekeneſſe and patience attend the Lordes leaſure,
<note place="margin">The applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer example.</note> wholie relying vpon his promiſes, which he knew ſhould be performed at ſuch time as God in his ſecrete counſell and foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge had determined. But you like wretches, and of all other moſt wretched, becauſe wilfullie wretched, liuing in a land wherein the heauens droppe downe fatneſſe, where honie diſtilleth from the ſtonie rocke: a lande not much inferiour to the lande of <hi>Canaan:</hi> a
<pb facs="tcp:9005:9"/>land much reſembling the happineſſe of <hi>Paradiſe;</hi> (as one of your owne complices lately confeſſed) liuing vnder the regiment of a vertuous Princeſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed Soueraigne; a Princeſſe euerie waye ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to <hi>Saule,</hi> and cannot by her greateſt enemies be impeached with any crime common to her with <hi>Saule:</hi> howbeit it was feared that <hi>Agag</hi> the Amalekite,
<note place="margin">Becauſe <hi>Saul</hi> ſpared <hi>Agag.</hi> God reiected <hi>Saul.</hi>
               </note> the profeſſed aduerſarie of Gods people ſhould haue béene ſpared: but (thanked be God) her louing ſubiectes to their generall reioycing are now diſburdened of that feare. A Princeſſe whoſe ſunbright honor dazeleth the eies of forraine Monarches; whoſe zealous inclination, like an ineſtimable Diamond enchaſed vpon a péereles Iewell, bewtifieth all other vertues that attend vpon her perſon; whoſe affectionate loue to her ſubiectes is wonderfull, paſſing the loue of <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; <hi>Ionathan;</hi> (and yet was their loue paſſing the loue of women) who tempereth iuſtice with mercie, extending mercie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out partialitie, and executing iuſtice without rigor: yet you through aboundance and proſperitie are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come wanton and inſolent;
<note place="margin">Fulneſſe is the mother of forgetfulnes and wealth nurſeth wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes.</note> through her too much grace and fauour ye are growne obdurate and rebellious; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuouring to ſupplant her, who ſtudieth to ſupport you; deuiſing her ouerthrowe, whoſe welfare is the ſureſt ankerhold to defend you from ſhipwracke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saule</hi> was reiected of God, yet durſt not <hi>Dauid</hi> annoye him: your dread ſoueraigne being legitimate heire and rightfull ſucceſſor, was both eſtabliſhed by God, and allowed by men; and is at this daie by his ſingular prouidence ſo miraculouſlye preſerued, that your wicked imaginations had ere this béen her deſtruction, and with her had manie thouſandes pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, and with them your ſelues (howſoeuer you perſwade your ſelues) had not he ouerſpread her with the reſplendiſant beames of his fatherly protection. But you will ſaie ſhée was excommunicated by <hi>Pius
<pb facs="tcp:9005:10"/>Quintus:</hi> (more truly might he be termed <hi>Impius</hi>) this obiection, though it might verie well haue béene an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered with ſilence, béeing ſo weake, lame, and out of ioynt as it is: yet hath it béene ſo throughly canua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſo plainelie confuted alreadie, that it hath good cauſe as much to be aſhamed of the patrones and defenders thereof, as they haue iuſt reaſon (had they anie reaſon at all) to bee aſhamed of it. Onely, of Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the thunderer of that excommunication, and of his equalles, the Popes I meane, (for of equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie otherwiſe, the Papacie is by all meanes impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and can no more tolerate a compéere, then the firmament can conteine two Sunnes: as one of their owne ſide full learnedly ſquared out the compariſon) thus much will I ſaie: <hi>Cui plus licet quàm par eſt, plus vult quàm licet:</hi> Hee that maie doo more then is méete, wil doo more then he maie.</p>
            <p>But to procéede: did not opportunitie of reuenge with vnfolded armes preſent her ſelfe to <hi>Dauid,</hi> at ſuch time as <hi>Saule</hi> vnaccompanied entered into the caue where <hi>Dauid</hi> with his aſſiſtants were aſſembled? <hi>Saule</hi> had often ſerued him with a crooked meaſure:
<note place="margin">In reuenging no man may be his owne car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er.</note> might hee not now haue meaſured to him by the ſame liſt? <hi>Saule</hi> had ſaluted him with manie croſſe curteſies: had he not now libertie to paie him home in his own coine, and to returne vſurie beſides the due debt? Had hee not abilitie to doo this? Naie, had hee not reaſon, if hee ſhould haue reaſoned with humane reaſon? No doubt <hi>Dauid</hi> managed a dangerous conflict, and like a Captaine moſt valiant, gaue the repulſe to aſſaults moſt violent, wherein loyall duetie contended with lawleſſe neceſſitie: and fleſhlie infirmitie combated with diuine ordinaunce. Deſire of a kingdome, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a courſe to compaſſe it with ſuch facilitie, is a plauſible Rhetorician, cunning to perſwade: (for,
<pb facs="tcp:9005:10"/>
               <hi>Si ius <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iolandum eſt, regni cauſa <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iolandum eſt:</hi> if the limittes of lawe maie bee infringed, then for a kingdomes cauſe maie they bee infringed) but aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of life beeing enuironed with manifeſt hazard of death, is a mightie Orator able to conuince. But as hee gaines a double conqueſt, that in conqueſt can conquere him ſelfe: ſo ſhall hee bee recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with treble puniſhment, that is by anie carnall perſwaſions entiſed, whether of benemous hatred, or honourable aduancement, or anie other thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, to accept of worldly benefite, and to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect heauenlie preſcription. If wee ſhall cenſure of the matter onlie according to ordinarie eſtimation, without queſtion the honour <hi>Dauid</hi> purchaſed by van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhing the Heatheniſh <hi>Golias,</hi> was not halfe ſo glorious, as that hee deſerued by ſubduing his owne thoughtes, in refraining to proffer violence to an annointed king. Which execrable offence if he had committed, it had excéeded both the adulterous abuſing of <hi>Barſabe,</hi> and the wrongfull murthering of <hi>Vrias,</hi> ſo much as a villanie practiſed againſt a Prince, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth an iniurie inferred to a priuate man.</p>
            <p>I thinke it not requiſite too much to inſiſt vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie particular circumſtance of the compariſon; but I would wiſhe you to weigh this with your ſelues. <hi>Dauid</hi> for feare withdrew himſelfe from <hi>Saules</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: ſome of you of malicious intent eſtrange your ſelues,
<note place="margin">The practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites &amp; S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> curſetting ouer like fugitiues into other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and there plant your ſelues in thoſe Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries, whoſe Gardener is Antichriſt, whoſe ſeedes are errors, whoſe fruites are treaſons. Where when you haue perfectly learned your leſſon, to tranſforme Chriſtian religion into prophane policie, and to change policie into trecherie; then like plantes of ſuch a ſoile, like pupilles of ſuch a Tutor, like Scollers of ripe wittes (yet not ſo ripe as rotten) yee turne ouer a
<pb facs="tcp:9005:11"/>new leafe, and from contemplation ye fall to practiſe; wherein ye ſo behaue your ſelues, that, as hee was reputed amongſt the barbarous Scythians the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt Gentleman that had committed the moſte bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſlaughters: ſo is hée amongſt you eſtéemed the notableſt Catholicke, that can bring moſt ſoules to confuſion. And then ye begin to imitate the Snake who caſtes off her olde coat, but retaines her olde poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſtill: ſo come ye diſguiſed in your habite marching on like Maſkers, hauing in ſtead of viſors ſhameles foreheads, and fronts vntaught to bluſh: but I would ye were Mummers, or els that your lippes were as ſurely ſealed and ſered as your conſciences are, with an hote iron: for then ſhould we by your ſignes giue a geſſe of your meaning. And though ye hoord vp ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome in your hearts, yet are your wordes ſmoother then oyle: though your ſpéeches be ſwéeter then honie, yet is the bitterneſſe of gall and wormewood hidden, yea, the poyſon of Aſpes lurketh vnder your lips. The Aſpe through the excéeding coldnes of his nature, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifieth the member that hée woundeth with his ſting. And therefore <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> at ſuch time as ſhée was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of her paramour <hi>Marcus Antonius,</hi> beeing wholie ouercome and ſwallowed vp with ſorrow, ſet two Aſpes to her breſtes, which benumming her ſenſes caſt her into a ſléep, into a dead ſléepe, euen into her laſt ſléepe. In like maner, you faſtening vpon thoſe that are as deuoutly addicted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh pots of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as euer the Egyptian Nueene was enamoured of <hi>Antonie,</hi> and yet ſeeming to haue queaſie ſtomackes, loath the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>Manna,</hi> accounting it a light meate, of euill nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment and hard digeſtion: ye ſtrike while the yron is hote, and finding them plyable to alteration, yee worke them like waxe, féeding their humors, and promiſing to reſtore their olde delightes: and ſo with your poyſoned perſwaſions, yée rocke ſome a ſléepe in ignorance; others
<pb facs="tcp:9005:11"/>ye bring to their lateſt ſleepe, and their longeſt home. This is the leauell of your deuiſe;
<note place="margin">The leauen of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ieſuites worſe then the leauen of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies.</note> this is the leauen of your doctrine. A litle of this leauen leaueneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole lumpe: and therefore let all ſtriue to purge out this lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, for there is no leauen like to this leauen, no, not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leauen of the Phariſies. But thoſe vp-ſtart marchants that bring ouer ſuch deceitfull drugges, are worthy to paye their heart-blood for cuſtome; the which howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer through their packing and conueyaunce they ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time auoide, let it not imbolden them in their vnbridled preſumptions, but let them feare (except they ſpéedily change their copy, &amp; heartily repent) leaſt the Almighty recompenſe theyr leauen with Leuin from heauen, and ſtrike them with flaſhing lightning, as he did <hi>Tullus Hoſtilius:</hi> yea, let them feare, leaſt the fire of his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation deuoure them, as the flame licketh vp the ſtuble, and leaſt he raine downe vpon them ſnares, fire, brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, ſtorme and tempeſt: for this is the portion of hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites.</p>
            <p>Yet if yee did thus deſiſt, and ſurceaſe from heaping vp the full meaſure of your wickednes, then ſhould not my ſoule be confounded with ſo great aſtoniſhment. But as the wilde Iuie creeping along on the grounde, beginneth at the firſt to imbrace the lower part of the Oke, and ſo cunningly climeth vp by degrées, till at laſt it ouerpéere the higheſt braunch, and then eating through the rinde pierceth to the inward pithe, ſucketh out the pureſt ſappe and naturall moiſture, to the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and decaying of the whole trunke: or as poiſon hauing attainted the leaſt member of the bodie, and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt diſtant from the heart, diſperſeth it ſelfe into the hidden paſſages of the veines, and beateth vp and down in euery path till it haue founde the high-way to the heart: where ſo ſoone as it is ſetled, it bendeth his force, and exerciſeth all violence, till it haue choked the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and raſed the foundation of life: ſo doo yée laye
<pb facs="tcp:9005:12"/>your platforme, firſt by paraſiticall inſinuation to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in the conſciences of inferiour perſons, hoping to fortifie your faction, by linking a multitude into the ſame confederacie: but the marke you ſhoote at, is the ſacred perſon of her maieſty. But before eyther your diſſembled zeale, or your gloſing flattery, or your dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poyſon, take ſo déepe roote, riſe to ſo full height, or breede ſo incurable a miſchiefe: your hope ſhall (I hope) be diſappointed, your ſelues ſhalbe rooted from y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> earth, and rotte in the ayre, that ſo your venome may returne into your owne boſomes. Neuer were the fennes of <hi>Lerna</hi> ſo daungerous: neuer was that monſter <hi>Hidra</hi> ſo pernicious, to the inhabitantes bordering and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereby: as the dennes of traitrous papiſts, and the deuiſes of that ſeuen-headed Romiſh Beaſt would prooue fatall to me and mine, if the puiſſant and victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Lion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tribe of <hi>Iuda,</hi> did not with vigilant eyes watch ouer vs for our defence, and with his outſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched arme vpholde vs from falling into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gaping iawes and bottomles gulfe of ſo rauening a bloodſucker. It is recorded in hiſtory, howe that notable robber <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> was accuſtomed to dragge cattell backwarde by the tayles into his Caue: to the ende that the print of theyr footing appearing contrary, he might eſcape free from ſuſpition of the theft: ſo is it your faſhion to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uegle diuerſe of thoſe whom you intend to make at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in your tragicall exploites, giuing them inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to practiſe popular demeanure, and carry a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of ordinary conformity,
<note place="margin">Papiſts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der holie lookes carrie hollow harts</note> howſoeuer they ſtand in heart affected to the truth, or infected with treaſon: ſhewing them ſelues in this point like to cunning wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-men, who caſt their eye one way, when they take theyr courſe another. The Lord will (I doubt not) in due time allot to ſuch halting <hi>ambodexters,</hi> ſucceſſe anſwerable to their ſiniſter meanings: that as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Flin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermouſe lighting into the Hawkes tala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, argued ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:9005:12"/>was in mouſe, by the proportion of her body: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter falling into the Cattes clawes, pleaded ſhe was a byrde by the fluttering of her winges: and was of the one diſdained, and of the other deuoured: ſo I wiſhe that ſuch hollowe hearted votaries as ſerue the time, but to ſerue theyr turne, lookinge when tyme will turne, that they may turne with time: might be tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly tryed, ſlowly truſted, but rather ſurely truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſo receiue a competent guerdon for theyr de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merites. And though they ſéeke to ſhaddow theyr pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes with a vayle of obſcuritye, and ſhuffle vp theyr actes <hi>in tenebris:</hi> yet if that carefull circumſpection be had, which the neceſſity of theſe times requireth, and the ſutlety of ſuch enimies importunately craueth, it wilbe a matter of no great difficultye, to diſcerne the Wolues, though they wander in ſheepes clothinge, by the noyſe of theyr howling: and to deſcrye the Aſſe, though he iette in the Lyons ſkinne, by the length of his eares. Yea, vnleſſe the multitude of our offences ſtop the courſe of Gods mercies, and eclypſe the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his fauour that hath ſo long ſhyned vpon vs, hee will ſo diſcloſe theyr whiſperinges in theyr ſecret chambers, that they ſhalbe preached on the houſe tops: he will cauſe the foules of the ayre, &amp; the beaſtes of the fielde to bewraye &amp; proclayme theyr driftes, manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting his glory in the preſeruation of his heritage, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of theyr aduerſaries. And as he broke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wheeles of the Egyptians Chariots, when they purſued the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites: ſo will hee daſhe in pieces all theyr engins, &amp; force them to crie out, as the Egyptians then did, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Wee will flee from the face of Iſraell,
<note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> for the Lorde fighteth for them againſt the Aegyptians.</hi> Then ſhall they that haue accepted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wages of vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, burſt out with <hi>Balaam</hi> into theſe words:
<note place="margin">Num. 23.</note> how ſhal we curſe, where God hath not curſed? or how ſhall we deteſt where the Lord hath not deteſted? Then ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:9005:13"/>their great Maſter for griefe of heart roare out with <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> the <hi>Apoſtata,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Viciſti Galilaee, viciſti:</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his ouerthrow to proceede from Chriſte, whom he hath as ſcornefully abuſed as euer did <hi>Julian;</hi> confeſſing him in word, but in heart denying him: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning the ſincerity of his goſpel, reproching the baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his humanity, deſpitefully perſecuting him in his members, &amp; (what in him lyeth) crucifying againe the ſonne of God.</p>
            <p>With this hope, as with a precious cordiall, doo I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort my languiſhing ſpirites: with this as with a ſoueraigne reſtority, doo I reuiue my fainting courage: with this as with a gentle emplaſter, doo I qualifie the rigor of my paſſionate and biting grieuances, knowing that he which kéepeth Iſraell, doth neither ſlumber nor ſleepe:
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 41.</note> but he will buſie <hi>Pharaos</hi> fantaſie with trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome dreames, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> releaſing of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> &amp; the ſuſtayning of <hi>Iacob:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſter. 6.</note> he will depriue <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> of his naturall reſt, for the deliuerance of Iſraell, &amp; the deſtruction of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> and notwithſtanding <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> command Gods children to be throwne into the fiery Furnace: yet ſhall the fire forget his property to burne, the flame ſhall forgoe his ſcorching heate, and alter th'effects pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by nature: his Angell ſhall with watchfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard miniſter vnto them, ſo that, not one hayre of their head ſhalbe burnt, neither their coates chaunged, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſmell of fire ſhall come vpon them. Though the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianites</hi> and <hi>Amalekites</hi> marſhall their forces,
<note place="margin">Iudic. 7.</note> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campe againſt the Lords people, like graſhoppers for multitude, and as the ſandes by the ſea fide, which are without number: yet will he giue <hi>Gedeon</hi> the victory, while they as men diſtract of their witts, ſhall broche the breſts of their neighbours and fellowes in armes with their owne ſwordes.
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 118.</note> 
               <hi>This is the Lords doing, &amp; it is wonderfull in our eyes.</hi> Wonderfull in deede, and paſſing wonderfull, if we behold it with fleſhly
<pb facs="tcp:9005:13"/>eyes, &amp; meaſure it by the leuell of carnall capacity: but if God ſharpen the eyeſight of our faith, then ſhall wee clearely perceiue, that he tendereth the ſafety of his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, as the apple of hie eye, &amp; cauſeth all his creatures to imploy theyr ſeruice to their behoofe: giuing withall his and their enimies to vnderſtand, that al wiſdome is fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and all ſtrength infirmitye, that is oppoſed againſt the Lord of hoaſtes.</p>
            <p>Now ſéeing the matter ſtandeth thus, tell me (yée per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe generation) with what hope doo yée caſt to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>triue ſo execrable purpoſes?
<note place="margin">Nauis ſtulto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> Now can yée expect a proſperous wind to land your veſſel at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſired hauen, ſéeing your ſhip is fraighted with ſuperſtition &amp; ballaſted with trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: ſuch trumperies as he that flyeth on the winges of the windes vtterly abhorreth? Why deſpiſe yée y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords holy temple in <hi>Ieruſalem?</hi> Why trudge yée ſo faſt vnto <hi>Dan</hi> to offer?
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 5.</note> why poſt yée from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Bethel</hi> to pleaſe <hi>
                  <hi>Ieroboam?</hi> Behold, to obaie is better then ſacrifice: and to hearken to the voice of God, is better then the fat of Rammes.</hi> How can <hi>Dagon</hi> the Idoll of the Philiſtines ſtand, where the Arke of God is in place? néedes muſt he fall flat to th'earth: and though the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous prieſts labour to erect him againe, yet ſhall his latter fall be more ſhamefull then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt: his head &amp; his hands ſhalbe cut of: he ſhall neither haue the reaſon, nor the power to lift vp himſelfe any more.
<note place="margin">The Pope compared to the Idoll of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines.</note> The <hi>Dagon</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Philiſtiues was ſaid to be like a man in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpper parts, but from the nauill downeward like a fiſhe: your <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> is neither fleſh nor fiſhe: but as he fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him ſelfe by bathing in the bloode of faithfull and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Martyrs: ſo maketh he all fiſh that comes to net, by faſhioning religion as may beſt ſerue to increaſe his reuenue, &amp; inrich his coffers. Whoſe miſhapen deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties if they were artificially pourtracted &amp; liuely depain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in freſh colours as an obiect for euery mans eie, then might I queſtion as the Poet did:
<pb facs="tcp:9005:14"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Spectatum admiſsiriſum teneatis amici?</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Frendes, had you leaue to looke your fill,</l>
                  <l>how could you chuſe but laugh?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Why then are yee ſo highly offended that <hi>Dagon</hi> is falne? why take ye it ſo at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heart, that I haue abridged his authority, &amp; emptied my caſk of ſuch ſtinking dregs? haue I done any other thing then caſt corrupted &amp; vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſalt on the dunghill, as his proper place? Therefore let me ſay vnto you, as <hi>Ioas</hi> ſaid to the men y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> were ſo fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly incenſed againſt <hi>Gedeon,</hi> for breaking down the altar of <hi>
                  <hi>Baal:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudic. 6.</note> will yee pleade <hi>Baals</hi> cauſe? or will yee ſaue him? he that will contend for him, let him die ere morning. If he bee God, let him pleade for him ſelfe againſt him that hath caſt downe his altar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> ſorrowed &amp; repented him ſelfe in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had cut off <hi>Saules</hi> ſkirt. O griefe to be commended ſo accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with grace. You ſtorme &amp; repine that you cannot cut ſhort the bloſſome of my ioy, &amp; glory of my garland. O griefe to be condemned ſo far paſt all grace. But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, repent euen while it is called too day: fall downe vpon the bended knees of your hearts before the Lords footeſtoole: with all humility and ſupplication ſue for grace at the throne of grace. Which vnles yée doo, know for a certainty, that as <hi>Dauids</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation dyeth not, ſo your condemnation ſléepeth not: only the Lord lifteth vp his hand on high, that he may inflict the déeper wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d when he ſtriketh.
<note place="margin">Obedience to Princes a principle in nature.</note> Now if this ſinguler example of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> pierce not your heartes with a godly remorſe, yet conſider that obedience to Princes is a principle in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who hath ingraued in euery mans mynde a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous impreſſion of duety in ſubiects towarde theyr ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes. Yea, ſhe hath inſtituted a lawe which the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnreaſonable creatures duely obſerue among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: as, the beaſtes giue place to the Lyon, and the foules yeelde reuerence, to the Eagle. Neyther hath there bene any nation ſo deſtitute of ciuility, wherein ſome one, eyther for that he was deſcended from royall
<pb facs="tcp:9005:14"/>parentage, or for the honorable opinion they conceiued of his vertues, obtayned not the greateſt titles of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and retained not the higheſt ſeate of preheminence. Though <hi>Iezebel</hi> were a woman of a vile diſpoſition, who repoſed her chiefe felicity in the performing of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; tyrannous actions: yet was not the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo quite extinguiſhed in her, but that ſhee iudged it an inexpiable offence to murther a lawfull King. For when <hi>Jehu</hi> the ſon of <hi>Nimſhi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> was by <hi>Elizeus</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to ſmite the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and to auenge the blood of the ſeruants and Prophets of the Lord: hauing ſlaine <hi>Iehoram</hi> (the younger ſon of <hi>Ahab,</hi> who raigned ouer <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the death of his brother <hi>Ahaziah</hi>) he came to <hi>Izreel,</hi> where <hi>Jezebel</hi> painting her face,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iezebel</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt Princes.</note> and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her head, looked out at the window, and ſayd: <hi>Had Zimri peace that ſlewe his maiſter?</hi> Which ſpéech, though it were grounded vpon a wrong coniecture: (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that burden was ſpecially layde vpon the houſe of <hi>Ahab</hi> by Gods appointment, and <hi>Iehu</hi> particularly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to that charge: whereas <hi>Zimri</hi> hauing no expreſſe warrant to ſhowe, went further then his commiſſion extended) yet it implyeth thus much, that ſhe thought it a moſt odious crime, &amp; was alſo perſwaded that ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance ſhoulde duely and continually attend vpon the ſame, euen at the hard heeles, as it had done vpon <hi>Zim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</hi> And therefore <hi>Jezebel,</hi> not able to diſcerne the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in thoſe deedes, nor to giue a diſtinction anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the natures of the facts, vpon premiſes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers quality, inferred probably, though indirectly, a ſem blable concluſion. For albeit the Lord by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mouth of his Prophet denounced dreadfull threatninges againſt the family of <hi>Baaſha:</hi> yet was not <hi>Zimri</hi> commaunded to conſpire againſt <hi>Elah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Baaſha,</hi> nor by killing of him to aſpire to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome, nor by incroching vpon the kingdome to roote out the ſtocke of <hi>Baaſha.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the treaſon that hee wrought againſt his Lorde and maiſter, the crueltyes hee practyſed agaynſt
<pb facs="tcp:9005:15"/>that houſe &amp; linage, were requited vnto him, at ſuch time as the hearts of the people being alienated from him, they conſented to abrogate that vſurped authority, as the birdes agreed to diſrobe <hi>Aeſopes</hi> dawe of his ſtolne plumes: and making <hi>Omri</hi> their generall, they went &amp; beſieged <hi>Tirzah,</hi> where <hi>Zimri</hi> kept him ſelfe in holde: which being taken, he for feare he ſhould haue faln into his enimies handes, fled into the kings pallace, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the houſe on fire burnt him ſelfe and ſo dyed.</p>
            <p>So then the difference to be noted betwene <hi>Iehu</hi> and <hi>Zimri</hi> is apparant inough. Whereof, whether <hi>Iezebel</hi> were in deede ignorant, or that ſhee did of ſet purpoſe compare <hi>Iehu</hi> to <hi>Zimri,</hi> either to dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite, or diſgrace him with the reproch of ſo infamous a compariſon: yet is this neceſſarily to be gathered, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhe accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the ſlaying of his natural annointed Prince, a thing moſt worthy all titles of opprobrious ignominy, &amp; all ſcourges of extreme reuenge.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iezebel</hi> ſhall ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours.</note> Shal not then <hi>Iezebel</hi> be iuſtified in reſpect of you? Nay, ſhal not <hi>Iezebel</hi> riſe in iudgement &amp; condemne you? And how ſhamefull will your ouerthrowe be, when the teſtimony &amp; verdit of ſo graceles a woman, ſhall ſtand in force againſt you: who (becauſe ye are birds of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame fether ſhe was of) would no doubt affourd you all poſſible fauor, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> indignity of your cauſe were capable of any colour or excuſe? What ſhall I thinke, what may I hope, or what muſt I not feare, if theſe examples drawne out of holy ſcriptures, worke not in you proportionall effect? If the word of God, which is ſo mighty in operation: which <hi>ſurpaſſeth in ſharpnes any two edged ſword:</hi>
               <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 4.</note> which <hi>entreth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen through to the diuiding in ſunder of the ſoule and the ſpirite, the ioints and the marrow:</hi> If (I ſay) it wound not your thoughts, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you ſtande as ſtill &amp; voide of ſenſe, as if it turned edge: then néedes muſt my wits be wrapped vp in amazement, &amp; my ſmiling hope be changed into chéerles feare: and where I perceiue the putrefaction to excéed all poſſibility of remedy by apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:9005:15"/>milde &amp; temperate medicines, there muſt I vſe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t means, ſharp corroſiues, yea, cauterie &amp; inciſion. And though you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne diuine oracles, yet wil not I refuſe to harken to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holeſom counſel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Peet where he ſaith:
<q>
                  <l>Cuncta priùs tentanda, ſed immedicabile vulnus</l>
                  <l>Enſe recîdendum, ne pars ſincera trahatur.</l>
               </q> 
               <hi>Which is,</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Trie firſt all waies to ſalue the ſore,</l>
                  <l>if cureles thou it ſee:</l>
                  <l>Then cut it off, leſt ſounder parts</l>
                  <l>therewith infected bee.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe ye ſo much affect the title of Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, looke a litle into the liues of ancient Romans, and you ſhal ſée how much ye come behind them in vertuous indeuours, and how far ye go beyond them in leude co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. At how light a price did <hi>Curtius</hi> value his life,
<note place="margin">The verie heathens haue preferred their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before their owne life.</note> when he threw himſelfe headlong into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peſtilent gulfe, which belched vp deadly corruption, &amp; breathed out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious vapours; which could not by any other means be ſtopped, but by caſting that iewel into it, which of all other vnder the Sun was moſt precious? Which thing when the Citizens of <hi>Rome,</hi> had with waſtfull loſſe of their treaſures in vaine aſſaied to effect, he knowing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could in worthines compare with mans ſoul, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily accorded to ſacrifice himſelf for the ſauegard of his countrey. What ſhould I talke of <hi>Mutius Scaeuola,</hi> who becauſe he failed in diſpatching <hi>Porſenna,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemie that ſought the wrack of his natiue citie, puniſhed that ouerſight in himſelfe, by conſuming his hand in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flame? To what end ſhould I record the inuincible magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of <hi>Horatius Cocles,</hi> who to withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the furious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſion of his countries foes, kept all alone the paſſage where the enemies gaue the aſſault, &amp; by his ſingle reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance gaue ſingular proofe of his incredible valor? what ſhould I ſtand to commend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honorable dealing of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>britius</hi> Conſul of <hi>Rome,</hi> to whom, during y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wars he held with <hi>Pirrhus</hi> king of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Epirotes,</hi> the kings phiſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made proffer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpon aſſurance of reward he would poiſon his
<pb facs="tcp:9005:16"/>maiſter: but <hi>Fabritius</hi> princely courage diſdaining to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere his enemie by intrapping him in ſnares of villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, preſently diſcloſed the matter to <hi>Pirrhus?</hi> God grant that all forren Princes may carry ſuch minds as <hi>Fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> did: and th'almightie defend my ſoueraign from all ſuch attendants as <hi>Pirrhus</hi> phiſician was: that no Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh breſt harbor any Spaniſh hart, nor ſubiects hand ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint it ſelfe with tempering Italian phiſicke. To be ſhort, what ſhall I need to extol <hi>Att. Regulus</hi> for his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted fidelitie, who hauing entred into ſolemne oath, either to ſend back the captiues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Carthage,</hi> or els to render himſelf priſoner into their hands: when be ſaw y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deliuery of the captiues would preiudice y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honor of his country, he was content rather to returne to his enemies, &amp; to indure moſt exquiſit torments, then either to make breach of his promiſe, or to infer detriment to the common wealth: thinking it better to end his life in torture as a faithfull captiue, then to prolong it in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure like a periured ſenator. I am y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more willing to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale &amp; paſſe ouer the application of theſe examples, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it doth redouble my ſorrows to think, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heathens ſhould ouercome Chriſtians: or Romanes Engliſhmen in pietie &amp; deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try. But (O vnſpeakable grief) I can neither find in you <hi>Curtius</hi> faith, nor <hi>Scaeuolas</hi> zeal, nor <hi>Horatius</hi> courage, nor <hi>Regulus</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancy. You at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt my deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, contrary to <hi>Curtius;</hi> you imagine your ſoueraigns death, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to <hi>Scaeuola:</hi> you deſire to bring in ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge forces, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to <hi>Horatius:</hi> you deny loi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie to your frends, wheras <hi>Regulus</hi> performed faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to his enemies. <hi>Regulus</hi> kept promiſe w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> his foes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he wold not indamage his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try: you break pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> your frends, &amp; enter league w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> your foes, becauſe ye wold ruinate your country. Unworthy therfore are ye to be numbred among ſuch men:
<note place="margin">Traitors are men in ſhape, but beaſts in behauiour.</note> vnworthy to liue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g chriſtian men: nay, vnworthy to carry y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> names of men, hauing litle in effect but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward ſhape of men. Ye haue defaced the beautie of humane nature, in defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb facs="tcp:9005:16"/>your minds with brutiſh behauior. Ye haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to weaue Spiders webbes, and to hatch Cocatrices egges. Ye haue lerned of the Tode to ſwell aboue natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral proportion: of the Wolfe to barke againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone: of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wilde Aſſe to braie againſt the thunder: of the Owle to eſchue the light of the Sun: and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Viper to gnaw through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bowels of your mother. Much more I might ſay, but I willingly refraine, leaſt my ſpéeches ſhould ſéeme rather to be diſtempered with partial choler, then ſeaſoned with louing affection.</p>
            <p>I could neuer yet vnderſtand that any traitor cloſed vp his laſt daies with honor, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> his gray haires went downe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graue in peace:
<note place="margin">The end of Traitors nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable.</note> but though for a time hée ſo floriſhed in pomp of worldly felicitie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> there might ſéem neither to haue bin place for better fortune, nor feare of worſe: yet was his iollitie nought els but grins to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle his deſires withall, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> being dronken w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exceſſe of vanitie, &amp; furfetting vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al varietie of pleſure, he might be pampred vp like an Oxe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in the ſtall is made fat for the ſlaughter. To which purpoſe if I ſhould begin to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, beſides y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I ſhould enter into a wide open field: I ſhould alſo light a candle at noone day, in reporting that wherof theſe times haue made you eiewitneſſes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I wil only point w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the finger at one or two exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forth of our own Chronicles: which, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they are in their kinde paſſing notable, ought not to be buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſilence. <hi>Richard</hi> the vſurper, raging like a foming Boare, ſought by force to open the waie to his wilfull &amp; inordinate deſire of ſoueraintie, ſparing neither age, ſexe, affinitie nor degrée, till hee had inueſted himſelfe with the regal Diademe, &amp; was then perſwaded that he had ſo firmely eſtabliſhed his regiment, that hee might without daunger giue fortune the defiance: yet ſée, a litle cloud riſing from the ſea, did on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſodaine ſo darken the Sunſhine of his deuiſes, that as one ſurpriſed with trembling feare, and wéelded in an endles Labyrinth, hée ſound no iſſue to wade through, but was affrighted
<pb facs="tcp:9005:17"/>with guiltie ſuſpicion by day, and terrified with fearful viſions by night: neither felt he any releaſe vntil death haſtned to demaund his right, &amp; to take iuſt reuenge vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. Who, though he were a king, yet being ſlain in the field was diſaraied of his armor &amp; robes, &amp; ſtript na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked was throwne ouerthwart a horſback with his face groueling to the earth: and ſo beſmeared with mire and gore was hurried from <hi>Boſworth</hi> to <hi>Leceſter:</hi> &amp; there in ſtead of funerall ſolemnities, he had black fame for his herault: ſhame for his ſhrouding ſhéete: &amp; neuer dying obloquie for his ſepulchre. Neither were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> executioners of his commaunds exempted from penaltie. For Syr <hi>Iames Tarrell</hi> (who was by him aduanced for the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the yoong king, his nephew) was in the raigne of king <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth beheaded at the Tower hill for treaſon.
<note place="margin">A vicious life endeth ſildom with a happie heath.</note> 
               <hi>Miles Forreſt</hi> péece-meale rotted away. <hi>Iohn Dightons</hi> death, though it be not certainly ſpecified, yet we may w<hi rend="sup">e</hi>out any breach of charitie ſuppoſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it was not greatly diſcrepant from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former courſe of his life.</p>
            <p>And no maruel if the Lord of hoſtes be ſo ielous ouer his Vicegerent, &amp; poure out ſuch rigorous puniſhments vpon archtraitors conſpiring againſt his annointed, ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he ſuffreth not petie trecheries, though in degrée far inferior, to eſcape vnreuenged. As may appear by <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Baneſter</hi> ſeruant to the Duke of <hi>Buckingham:</hi> who though he were brought vp vnder the Duke, &amp; had from him receiued many benefites: yet at ſuch time as the Duke being encountred with great extremities, and on euery ſide maruellouſly diſtreſſed, committed his life to <hi>Baneſters</hi> ſecrecie, thinking it the ſafeſt refuge and ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary that he could repaire vnto: <hi>Baneſter</hi> in expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the reward that was promiſed by proelamation to him that could diſcouer him, readely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſcended to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraie his Lord. But ſhortly after it came to paſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> his ſonne and heire fell mad &amp; died in a Bores ſtie: his eldeſt daughter was ſtriken with leproſie: his ſecond ſonne was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lame, &amp; his yoongeſt ſon drowned in a pudle: &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:9005:17"/>laſtly <hi>Baneſter</hi> himſelfe was arraigned for murther, and with much adoe eſcaping, was fruſtrated of that golden recompence which he preferred before his Lords life, and his owne reputation. I ſpeake not this to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage the Dukes action, the equitie of whoſe cauſe I refer to the cenſure of the wiſe, but ſéeing all déeds are to be meaſured by the intent of the doer, and the ſequele of the fact, néeds muſt he be noted for a faithles caitife that began his action in wretched auarice, and ended it in ſhamefull miſerie. If I ſhould draw theſe and ſuch like particulars into the forme of an induction, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon grounding a generall concluſion ſhould ſay, that neuer traitor to his prince atchiued happie and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous end, I thinke it would be hard for you to giue an inſtance to the contrarie: vnles haply you pleaſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, by nominating any of the ſtragling extrauagants,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ieſuites</hi> by profeſſion are in condition <hi>Iſcariotes.</hi>
               </note> that carying the title of <hi>Ieſuites</hi> lead the liues of <hi>Iſcariots,</hi> and either by raunging abroad, or diſſembling at home, chance to eſcape the whip. But they muſt imagine that forbearance is no quittance, and the longer they run on the ſcore, the harder will the reckoning proue when it comes to paiment. Howſoeuer one traitor liſt to deſcant vpon the fall of another, imputing his ouerthrow to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſes, aſcribing it to fatall influence, and angrie ſtars: wreſting it either to want of pollicie, or neglect of opportunitie; or default of ſecreſie; or his too much care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſnes, or his too litle courage; and with theſe vaine il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtons flatter his conceite, hoping that he ſhal ouerleap that ſtumbling blocke whereat his fellow traitor broke his necke: though debating the matter with himſelfe, he impart his purpoſe to no other: yet may he be ſure, that he whoſe eies are as flames of fire: who ſearcheth the hart, and the reines: who bringeth light out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: to whom darknes is no darknes, but the night is as cleare as the day: he may be ſure (I ſay) that he both can &amp; will at his good pleaſure bewraie him for the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of his glorie, and maintenance of his annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
<pb facs="tcp:9005:18"/>Therefore if I may either command as a mother, or intreat as a friend, or avuiſe as a wel willer; if either the declining courſe of my yeares may plead pitie, or the ſinceritie of my meaning gains credit, or my experience in miſeries giue direction; let theſe wordes, which my fainting breath and faultring tongue can ſcarcely vtter, dehort you from proſecuting thoſe villanies that ye haue wickedly attempted, and forewarn you to auoid that peril ye haue deſperately incurred.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould recount the benefits that from time to time I haue ouer prodigally beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, I doubt I ſhould ſooner weary my ſelfe with the reherſall, then bréed in you any thankfull acknowledgement of the ſame.
<note place="margin">Eſt aliqua ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to meritum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrare vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptas.</note> Yet becauſe it ſomewhat eaſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomacke, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrate to vngrateful perſous good turns paſt; I muſt affirme that which you can not deny, that ſince <hi>Brute</hi> firſt ſet foot within my ſhore, I neuer was indowed with ſo bountifull bleſſings, neuer more deckt with or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of peace, neuer leſſe trauailed with incombran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of war: ſo that I may confidently auouch, that mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie &amp; trueth are met together; righteouſnes &amp; peace haue kiſſed each other: truth hath floriſhed out of the earth, &amp; righteouſnes hath looked down from heauen. But if ye looke a litle abroad, ye may ſée others toſſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raging tempeſts; whereas your ſelues ſtand on the ſhore not threatned by any ſuch ieopardy: you triumph in garla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Oliue, when your neighbors are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to weare the wreathes of Cypres:
<note place="margin">Deus nobis haec otia fecit.</note> and you may ioyfully ſing <hi>Te Deum</hi> in the higheſt note, when they (God knoweth) are faine to cry <hi>Miſerere</hi> in a mournful voice. The nations round about you are infeſted with martiall horror, with clattering of armour, with thundring of ſhot, with ſhrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of women, wailing of children, ſlaughter of men, deſolation of prouinces,
<note place="margin">Amos. 6.</note> &amp; infinite ſuch ſpectacles of dread and terror. But <hi>you haue ſtretched your ſelues vpon beds of iuorie, ye haue eate the lambes of the flock, &amp; calues of the ſtall; ye haue ſung to the ſound of the
<pb facs="tcp:9005:18"/>viole, &amp; inuented to your ſelues inſtruments of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke: ye haue drunke your wine in bowles, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed your ſelues with the coſtlieſt ointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: but who among you hath beene ſorie for the affliction of Ioſeph?</hi> who hath called his impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance? who among you hath not ſought to throw him into the dungeon againe? or which of you hath nor gone about to trouble <hi>Iſrael?</hi> and <hi>as ye haue increaſed in iol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litle, ſo haue ye multiplied in tranſgreſsion:
<note place="margin">Hoſea. 4.</note> therfore will the Lord turne your glorie into ſhame.</hi> Ye haue couertly girded your loines with the weapons of war in the time of peace, intending if opportunitie had ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued your purpoſe,
<note place="margin">2. Sim. 3.</note> to doe to your brethren as <hi>Ioab</hi> did to <hi>Abner,</hi> when he flatteringly embraced him with the one hand, &amp; cruelly with the other gaue him his deathes wound. Ye haue peruerted the courſe of nature in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing troublſom ſtormes to ariſe in the golden daies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Alcyon.</hi> In déed I confeſſe it is an impeſſible thing that light ſhould make agréement with darkeneſſe, or truth haue ſociety with error. The mortall hatred &amp; vnappea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention,
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 25.</note> that inſued betwixt <hi>Iacob</hi> &amp; <hi>Eſau</hi> was not obſcurely prognoſtieated at their natiuitie, when they ſtroue and wreſtled together in <hi>Rebeccaes</hi> wombe, to the great diſcomfort of her ſoule. The rooted enimitie that you carry againſt the profeſſors of the Goſpel,
<note place="margin">The coles of hatred that Papiſts rake by in their brells muſt needs vent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſmoke of ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orts</note> howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be raked vp in the deceiptfull cinders of counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit amitie, yet doth it ſo vehemently ſtriue to burſt out, that if it ſhould not find a louerhole and place of vent to iſſue forth by the ſmoke of ſlandrous reports &amp; fabulous rumors (which are commonly coined for the nouriſhing of diſcouragement and falſe ſuſpicions in true ſubiects harts) it would ſo ſcald and bliſter your lips, that by the ſame as by a certaine cogniſance we might deſcry you. In your harts you euer follow the faſhion of the Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that delights to fly againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wind: in your ſpéeches you play the Lapwing, that flickereth a looſe in a place ſome what diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her neaſt, to withdraw the paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers thence.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9005:19"/>
            <p>The Poets pleaſantly deuiſe that when <hi>Iupiter</hi> had made man, glorying in the workemanſhip thereof, he brought him to find-fault <hi>Momus,</hi> and demanded what he could eſpie in him worthy reprehenſion: <hi>Momus</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the orderly feature and ſéemely diſpoſition of the lineame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: but one thing (ſaith he) I greatly diſlike, that thou haſt forgotten to frame a window in his breſt, whereby it might be known whether his hart and his tongue went together or not. If the conſciences of trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torous Papiſts might be as througly ranſackt, and as déeply ſounded, as they may be iuſtly doubted, there would be found cakes of foule cankered malice, &amp; long feſtred choler buried vnder painted hoods, &amp; mealemou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed proteſtations. Then would the grutchings &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings of <hi>Eſau</hi> come to light,
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 27.</note> who threatned to ſlay his brother <hi>Iacob</hi> after the daies of mourning were finiſht. But take ye héed to your ſelues, leſt the miſchiefe ye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend againſt others, be in the end deriued vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your own pates. For it often times commeth to paſſe that God ſnareth the wicked in their proper inuentions, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth them by the ſame meanes whereby they offend. <hi>Thomyris</hi> quéene of <hi>Scithia,</hi> after ſhe had vanquiſhed <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> ſmote off his head, and threw it into a veſſel of blood, ſaying: <hi>Now drinke thou blood thy belly full, which thou haſt hitherto ſo much thirſted after. <hi>Craſſus</hi>
               </hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flaine in the expedition againſt the <hi>Parthians,</hi> they tooke molten gold and poured it into his mouth, ſaying: <hi>Now glut and accloie thy ſelfe with gold,
<note place="margin">Iudic. 1.</note> wherwith thy vnſtaunched hunger was neuer yet ſatiſfied.</hi> And when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had taken <hi>Adoni-bezek,</hi> they cut off the thumbes of his hands, and the great toes of his féet: wherupon he confeſſed, ſaying: <hi>Seuentie kings haning the thumbes of their hands and of their feet cut off, gathered bread vnder my table: as I haue done, ſo God hath rewarded me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your deſire is to erect a freſh the pageant of papiſtrie; and for the compaſſing thereof, ye are willing, not onely
<pb facs="tcp:9005:19"/>to contribute your bracelets &amp; earerings to the making of the golden calfe,
<note place="margin">Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as the idolatrous childrent of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did: but ready alſo to offer your ſons in ſacrifice, as the vnnaturall king of <hi>Moab</hi> did,
<note place="margin">2. Reg 3.</note> to pacifie his incenſed Gods: naie,
<note place="margin">The Papiſts are content to hazard theyr liues for the reſtoring of the Romiſhe Religion.</note> contented to make your owne liues a prate as the <hi>Athenians</hi> did, when they accorded by caſting of lottes to ſurrender themſelues to be deuoured of that hideous monſter <hi>Minotaurus.</hi> Thoſe among you that haue rotted in the corruption, and wallowed in the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of their opinions, longing with the dogge to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to theyr olde vomite, deſerue to be laughed at for their madnes: concerning whome we may cry out with the Prophet: <hi>Is there no baulme at <hi>Gilead?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 8.</note> is there no Phiſicion there? why then is not the health of the daughter of my people healed?</hi> And thoſe maie be compared to the <hi>Scarabie,</hi> which beeing bred in the dunghill proſpereth there exceeding well: but if ſhée happen to ſettle vnder the roſe trée, ſhe dieth inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The other that neuer ſawe papiſtrie in his higheſt ruffe, but through the ſeducing of their olde maiſters, haue bene brought to the bent of their bow, are to be pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied for their follie: of whome we may ſay with the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, that they may ſeeme to haue ſucked error out of theyr Nurſes breſtes with the verie milke of theyr in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie; and theſe are like the fooliſh flie that dallieth ſo long with the candle, till ſhee ſenge her winges in the flame: theſe playe as did the fond <hi>Satyre,</hi> who eſpying the fire that <hi>Prometheus</hi> firſt brought downe from heauen, would needes kiſſe it becauſe it gliſtered in hys eyes. Both theſe ſortes iointly conſidered, reſemble that ſottiſh <hi>Grillus;</hi> who, when he with the reſt of his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions had by the polliticke and ingenious ſtratageme of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes</hi> eſcaped from out the denne of that deformed Ciclop <hi>Polyphemus,</hi> would needes haue gone back, with the hazard of his life to haue recouered his girdle that he left behind him. And beeing afterwardes in the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:9005:20"/>voiage by the inchantments of <hi>Circes</hi> chaunged into the forme of an hog refuſed to return to the ſhape of a man. The pope is that monſter and aſtoniſhment of nature, who hath ſo long inchained chriſtian ſoules in miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thraldome and more then Egiptian ſeruitude,
<note place="margin">The Romiſh Religion more infected with errors then <hi>Augaeus</hi> ſtable was filled with ordure.</note> where they haue continued lockt vp in his darkeſome dungeon as in the ſhadow of death: which is more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plentiſht with ordure then <hi>Augaeus</hi> ſtable, and therefore requireth a mightier and more puiſſant champion to purge it then <hi>Hercules</hi> was. He is that abhominable ſtrumpet that ſo long beſotted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world with her witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craftes and ſorceries; that made <hi>The kings and inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the earth dronken with the wine of her fornication.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apocal. 17</note> But <hi>in the hand of the Lord there is a cup and the wine is red, it is full mixt, &amp; he poureth out of the ſame:
<note place="margin">Pſalme. 75.</note> ſurely all the wicked of the world ſhal wring out and drinke the dregs therof.</hi> If all the wicked ſhall drink of it, then of all the moſt wicked, in reſpect of whom <hi>Ieroboam</hi> may be reputed for righteous, he, euen he of all others y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt wicked, ſhal haue a large draught for his ſhare, he ſhall turne off a full carouſe.</p>
            <p>If ye would but faſten your eyes vpon me a while, ye might in my forehead eaſilie reads what woulde be your own deſtinies vnder his gouernment. For though time hath healed the wounds with which he deſpitefully mangled my body yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſkars and blemiſhes remain ſtil behind. My meaning is, there yet liueth many a one, whoſe father, mother, brother, ſiſter, kinſman or friend, this ſauage Antichriſt hath wrongfully murthered, &amp; by vntimelydeath abridged y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> date of theyr days; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fiſcating their goods, and leauing their poſterity not onely father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les children, but alſo comfortles orphans. When I look back to the calamity of thoſe times, I féele my poore hart begin to reſolue into ſtreams of blood, &amp; mine eyes melt into flouds of teares, at the onely remembrance thereof; euen as the carcaſe of a murtherd man guſheth forth
<pb facs="tcp:9005:20"/>into bléeding at the preſence of the murtherer. <hi>Hercules</hi> when he came vp from hel, looking back at the wonderful dangers that he had waded through, ſhooke for ioy. And how can I but reioyce with trembling before my Lord God, who hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off my purple garment, and clothed me with a white robe; who hath wiped away the teares from mine eies, and crowned me with ioy and gladnes? Therefore bleſſed be my Lord y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hath greeted his ſpouſe with this conſolation: <hi>Behold winter is paſt,
<note place="margin">Cant. 2.</note> the ſtorm is blown ouer, &amp; gone awaie.</hi> Yea, for euer magnified he his name that hath reſpected the lowly eſſate of hys handmaid. How might I now expreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moitie of grief that I then felt when my boſome was bedewed with the warim blood of guiltles martirs? when reuerent old age wanted due obſequies?
<note place="margin">Theſe things are too true to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, and to apparant to be diſſembled.</note> when flouring youth was cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les cropt in his prime? when womans weaknes was not ſpared, no, not the woman with child? but (O more then barbarous cruelty) when the infant ſpringing out of the mothers wombe was thrown againe into the fire? what ſhould I ſpeake of burning the hands of perſons vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned? or of priuie ſlaughters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted in priſons? ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former example I doubt whether <hi>Phalaris</hi> hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (if he had then liued) could haue added ame thing for the aggrauating of their tiranny. Thinke with your ſelues how I groned vnder the importable waight of ſo lamentable diſtreſſes: which if they did then craze my hart, they would now force it to breake in ſunder.</p>
            <p>But (as <hi>Capnio</hi> ſaid) <hi>quum duplicarentur lateres, tum venit Moſes:</hi> when <hi>Pharao</hi> cauſed the taſk of brick to be doubled, then came <hi>Moſes.</hi> And when burdens begin to grow ouergrieuous, then ariſeth vp deliuerance. When y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Philiſtines</hi> offred ſacrifice to their God <hi>Dagon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudic. 16.</note> ſcoffing and inſulting at the miſerie of <hi>Samſon,</hi> whoſe eyes they had before bored out, then was their comical paſtime in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terturbed with a tragicall concluſion: the houſe came tumbling on theyr heads, &amp; God made him their ſcourge
<pb facs="tcp:9005:21"/>whome they made theyr game.
<note place="margin">Prouerb. 16.</note> For <hi>pride goeth before deſtruction and a high mind before a fall:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 18.</note> and <hi>could it be that God ſhoulde not auenge his elect which cried daie and night vnto him, yea, though hee ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them long?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>When <hi>Neſſus</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>Centaure</hi> intending to rauiſh <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neira,</hi> had receiued his deathes wound for his hire at <hi>Hercules</hi> hand, he then beſought her of pardon, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſemblance of great ſorrow, he gaue her of his blood, enioyning her to reſerue it as a rare monument and riche treaſure, the vertue whereof hee ſaid was inualu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: for therby ſhee might at her pleaſure reclayme the wandering affection of her huſband, if hee ſhould chance at any time through diſtoialtie to eſtraunge himſelfe from her companie. Of which thing ſhee afterward making triall, waſhed his ſhirt in the bloud, which ſo ſoone as he had at vnawares put on, he was therewith poyſoned. In like caſe the Pope indeuouring to deſpoile the Church of England of her dignities by incroche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and intruſion; and to curtoll the prerogatiue of the royall ſtate by vſurpation: had in a happie houre both the check and the mate giuen him; wherupon he almoſt in vtter deſpair of filling vp ſo great a breach, hath ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered abroad his lying ſpirites to inueigle our malcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Romaniſtes, to reuolt from obeyſance, warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them by force of his abſolution, as by <hi>Neſſus</hi> bloud, to rectifie all imaginarie and ſuppoſed iniuries, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they ſhal find themſelues neuer ſo little agreeued: and thus doe they (you I meane) practiſe to execute this deuiſe: but (thanks be giuen to our mercifull God) to your own ſubuerſions. The differences are: what <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aneira</hi> did was vpon ignorant zeale: what you doe is vpon peſtilent rancour. <hi>Hercules</hi> imbraced ſtrange loue contrarie to dutie: but her Maieſtie tendereth you farre aboue your deſertes.</p>
            <p>But leaſt I might be thought to compoſe clamorous
<pb facs="tcp:9005:21"/>inuectiues againſt the Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> not ſufficiently poized with their iuſt moments of reaſon; I wil alledge ſome ſpecialties for the confirming of my aſſertion. As touching the ſcope of their doctrine, becauſe it is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not wholie incident to the meannes of my caparitie, and ſomewhat without the compaſſe of this diſcourſe, I purpoſely relinquiſh it. Howbeit if I ſhould deſcend to the diſcuſſing of particularities I coulde challenge him of many ſciſmaticall points built vpon humane tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and repugnant to the veritie of holie Scriptures. For howe hath hee inferſed his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to continue the wodden worſhipping of images? to the whiche I may (not vnfitly) applie the poeticall <hi>Ironie,</hi> which is vſed againſt the Egiptians that adored Oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Garlike, as the Papiſts do trees and ſtocks:
<q>
                  <l>O ſanctae gentes quibus innaſcuntur in hortis Numina.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>O holie people they whoſe Gods</l>
                  <l>Within their Gardens grow.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>How hath he multiplied Mediatours, making ſome of ſaluation, others of interceſſion; derogating from the office of Chriſt, to maintain y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inuocation of Saints? whereas the Scripture preciſely deſigneth one, ſaying: <hi>There is one God,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> and one mediatour betwene God and man, which is the man Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> How hath he foiſted in his diſtinction of mortall and veniall ſinnes, to prop his Purgatorie that is now ſo ruinous for lack of reparation? We are taught in Gods worde, that all ſinnes are venial in Chriſt, except the ſinne againſt the holie Ghoſt: (which is therefore called of Saint <hi>
                  <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 5. Rom. 6. Marc. 3.</note> a ſinne vnto death</hi>) and all mortall in theyr owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>For the wages of ſinne is death.</hi> And, <hi>all ſinnes ſhalbe forgiuen vnto the children of men, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies wherewith they blaſpheme: but hee that blaſphemeth againſt the holie Ghoſt, ſhal neuer haue forgiuenes, but is culpable of eternall damnation.</hi> Theſe may ſerue to giue you a taſte, ſéeing it ſtands not
<pb facs="tcp:9005:22"/>with my purpoſe to frame any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſial treatiſe: but ye may geſſe the beaſt by his paw. In generall this is to be obſerued in their doctrine, that they when they are had in chaſe, they haue ſo manie muces, inturninges: winding corners, and ſtarting holes, that but for the tracke of their footing it were hard to ouertake them. In their intricate ſophiſines &amp; inexplicable quiddities, they play like the fiſh called the <hi>Cuttle,</hi> which when the fiſherman is readie to lay hand vpon her, caſteth forth a ſlimis blacke humour like vnto inke, which darkening the vpper face of the water, cauſeth the fiſherman to fayle of hys ayme, and by that meanes ſhe eſcapeth: and I may ſay of them as <hi>Ceſar</hi> ſayd of the <hi>Scithians</hi> whoſe maner it was to lurke in vncouth thickets: <hi>Difficilius eſt inuenire, quàm ſuperare:</hi> It is an harder matter to find them out then to ouercome them.</p>
            <p>Touching his gouernement, it is nothing elſe but a mightie faction of men, and armed power of Princes bending their forces directly agaynſt the Goſpell of peace. Howe intollerable is his ambition that arroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to himſelfe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſalitie,</hi> truſting to draw not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <hi>Iordan</hi> like the <hi>Behemoth,</hi> but the foure quarters of the world into hys mouth?
<note place="margin">Iob. 40.</note> And yet behold his ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hipocriſie,
<note place="margin">The Pores ambitious pride ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with a ſhow of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</note> who claiming ſupreme iuriſdiction in al cauſes, and throughout all Countries, yet vaileth bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, and abaſeth hys ſtile calling himſelfe <hi>ſeruum ſeruo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Dei.</hi> Of which diſſembled humilitie this <hi>Diſtich</hi> was compiled, not altogether vnworthie the rehearſal.
<q>
                  <l>Roma tibi quondam ſuberant Domini dominorum,</l>
                  <l>Seruorum ſerui nunc tibi ſunt Domini:</l>
               </q> 
               <hi>Which is</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Time was <hi>(O Rome)</hi> when Lords of Lords,</l>
                  <l>to thee did becke and bowe:</l>
                  <l>Time's paſt: and ſeruantes ſeruantes are</l>
                  <l>thy Lordes and maiſters now.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Hath he not always vnder a colour of pietie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, broched moſt impious and leaſt religious practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes?
<pb facs="tcp:9005:22"/>So that long ſince the <hi>Germanes</hi> perceiuing hys iugling, howe he foſtered contentions, cloked murthers wincked at hereſies, and diſpenſed with all crimes how capitall ſo euer, if he might thereby either dilate his ſeg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niories, or furniſhe his treaſurie, reiected his pretenſed aucthoritie: and marking howe outragiouſly hee ſet vp his briſtles and whetted his tuſkes againſt ſuch as croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his deuiſes, anathematiſing them with the horrible curſſe of <hi>Shimei,</hi> and ratling out his excommunications againſt them, they both ſharply reprooued and openly derided his Bulles before the which he was accuſtomed to prefix the name of the almightie, moſt blaſphemouſly making it to leade the waye to his diueliſh execrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: ſo that it became amongeſt them a common by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worde: <hi>In nomine Dei incipit omne malum:</hi> all miſchiefe beginnes in Gods name. And to gleane a fewe eares out of a full ſheafe, I will ſet downe ſome ſeuerall examples. In the tyme of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ninth, ſprang vp the diuiſion of the <hi>Guelfes</hi> and the <hi>Gibellines:</hi> the <hi>Guelfes</hi> bolſtering out the ſwelling inſolencie of the Popedome, and the <hi>Gibellines</hi> aſſiſting the iuſt title of the imperiall maieſtie. Through the whiche occaſion, moſte tumultuous vprores and deadly warres were arreared: the furie wherof being ſcarſe calmed &amp; allaied within one hundred yeares after, hath left a perpetuall memorie to the world,
<note place="margin">How the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Elſes &amp; Goblins firſt came vp.</note> by thoſe tearmes of elfes &amp; gob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins, that are at this day more generally knowne then rightly vnderſtood. During which faction <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight aſpired to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sea: who beeing maliciouſly inflamed agaynſt the families of <hi>Columne</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſini,</hi> becauſe they fauoured the <hi>Gibellines,</hi> wrought them all poſſible deſpite, in putting theyr bodyes to the ſword, their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to the ſacke, and theyr goodes to the ſpoyle. And ſo irreconcilable was this his wrath that on Aſhwed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſprinckled aſhes on his <hi>Cardinalls</hi> heads, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to <hi>Porcherus</hi> Archbiſhoppe of <hi>Genna,</hi> who was
<pb facs="tcp:9005:23"/>of the <hi>Gibellines,</hi> whereas he had vſed theſe words to the others: <hi>Memento homo quod cinis es, &amp; in cinerem reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>têris:</hi> That is; Remember man that thou art aſhes and into aſhes thou ſhalt returne:
<note place="margin">Here was a hote ſtomacke and colde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion.</note> a ſodaine fit of che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler boiling in his ſtomack, cauſed him to forget the depth of his deuotion, and alter the forme of his ſpeeche; ſo that throwing the aſhes into the Archbiſhops face, hee bluſtred out in theſe terms; <hi>Memento homo quod Gibelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus es, &amp; cum Gibellinis moriêre:</hi> Remember fellowe that thou art a <hi>Gibelline,</hi> and with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Gibellines</hi> thou ſhalt to the pot. <hi>Deus bone, tantaenè animis coeleſtibus irae?</hi> Good God, can holie heades harbour ſuch rancorous hatred?</p>
            <p>How miſchieuouſly did <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth conſpire with the ſtates of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> againſt <hi>Henrie</hi> the fourthe Emperour of <hi>Germanie,</hi> when commencing quarrell againſt him, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uented him of hereſie, for beſtowing eccleſiaſticall promotions vpon perſons both inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for theyr giftes, and defamed for theyr behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours? and ſentencing againſt hym, hee adiudged him to doe dayly penaunce at the Churche-dore of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paule,</hi> for the ſpace of one whole yeare. Moreouer he inforced hym barefooted and barelegged to creepe to kiſſe his feete. And during this turmoyle, hee ſuborned <hi>Rodolphe</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxonie</hi> to inuade the Empire: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Emperour beeing aduertiſed, thought it was nowe high tyme to reſiſte ſo daungerous a practiſe, and haſting into <hi>Germanie</hi> hee encountred <hi>Rodolphe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A guiltie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is a biting corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue.</note> and in fiue ſeuerall battayles diſcomfited him. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphe</hi> ſhortlie after lying on his deathe bed, was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with hys owne hand that had beene ſmitten off in fight. Whiche when he behelde, turning hys face to the Biſhoppes that ſtoode about hym, hee ſayd: This is the right hand, wherewith I vowed my fayth to the Emperor; now is the ſame become a witneſſe of my breach of fidelitie, and traiterous attemptes againſt my ſoueraign: chiefly by your, euen by your inſtigation
<pb facs="tcp:9005:23"/>and procurement, my Lords. If I might without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſpurre the Pope a queſtion, I would faine know whether <hi>S. Peters</hi> keyes hang (as he ſaith) at his girdle for that end to barre the gates of vnitie, and open the doores of diſſenſion? If there be a bleſſing laide vp in ſtore for the peacemakers, let him tell me what ſhalbe the reward of ſuch as kindle coles of mutinie and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Eſpecially ſéeing he is in double fault that giueth offence by his example. Was not the preſumption of <hi>Alexander</hi> the third vnmeaſurable, and the pride Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer-like, that he exerciſed againſt the Emperour <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericke,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Barbaroſſa,</hi> vpon whoſe backe when he had ſet the ſtates of <hi>Italie</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice,</hi> and alſo capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated <hi>Otto</hi> the Emperours ſonne, working vpon this aduantage he conſtrained him to yéeld to ſuch vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable condicions, as better agréed with his impudent and vaineglorious nature to demaund, then with <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derickes</hi> magnanimitie to condeſcend vnto. So that he was driuen to proſtrate himſelfe in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice</hi> at the Popes féete; and yet he not contented with this, more then humble ſubmiſſion, contumeliouſly trode vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his necke, abuſing that text of ſcripture:
<note place="margin">Pſalme. 91.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <hi>Super Aſpidem &amp; Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſcum, &amp;c.</hi> Thou ſhalt walke vpon the Adder and the Baſiliske, the yong Lion and the Dragon ſhalt thou tread vnder thy feet.</hi> The Emperor ſéeing himſelfe ſo diſdainefully ouercrowed by a dunghill crauen, could not ſuppreſſe his heroicall ſtomacke, but anſwered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; <hi>Non tibi ſed Petro:</hi> I doe this in reuerence of <hi>Peter,</hi> and not for feare of thée. Whereat the Pope ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, with open mouth intercepted his wordes excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, <hi>Et mihi &amp; Petro:</hi> thou ſhalt dos this reuerence both to <hi>Peter</hi> and me. This ruffling champion was (no doubt) profoundly inſtructed in the ſchoole of Chriſt;
<note place="margin">Mat. 12.</note> whoſe lowlineſſe was ſuch that <hi>he brake not the bruiſed reede, nor quenched the ſmoking flaxe:</hi> he reproued his Diſciples, when they would haue had
<pb facs="tcp:9005:24"/>fire to come down from heauen and conſume the <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc. 11. Mat. 11.</hi> Chriſtes ſchoole is of humilitie: but the Pope may be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out for a <hi>non profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ient.</hi>
               </note> ſaying: <hi>Ye know not of what ſpirite ye are.</hi> He willed them to learne of him: <hi>For I am</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>lowlie and meeke: and ſo ſhall ye find reſt to your ſoules.</hi> What ſhould I rehearſe the broiles, wherewith <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> the ninth peſtered <hi>Frederike</hi> the ſecond? who for that in a cauſe which admitted no dilatorie circumſtance, but as it imported matter of ſinguler conſequence, ſo it required meanes of preſent expedition, for that (I ſay) he departed without taking ſolemne farewell &amp; humble leaue of the Popes holines, hauing leuied a ſupply of ſouldiours to paſſe into <hi>Aſia</hi> for reſkuing of the diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſtians in their wars againſt the Saraſens, he was retracted by the Popes countermaund, that he ſent to the Chriſtian armie ſtraightly interdicting them to follow the Emperous conduct: neither could he by any interceſſion obtaine releaſe, vntil he had throwne a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſop into <hi>Corberus</hi> iawes, and ſtopt the Popes mouth with paiment of an hundred and twentie thouſand ounces of gold.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being ſo plaine that they can not be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſhadowed with anie pretence, me thinkes the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters anſwere was reaſonably framed, that he made in defence of his workemanſhip: who being checkt becauſe he dad drawne the counterfeit of <hi>S. Peter</hi> too high colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, whome they affirmed to haue béene of pale counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, foreworne with carefull vigilancie and paineful trauaile, which he alwaies tooke about his paſtorall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires &amp; Apoſtolicall negotiations: I haue (ſaid he) made him not as he was on earth, but as he is now in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: from whence looking down into the liues of his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, he bluſheth for ſhame to ſée their ſhameleſſe miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanure. And as the Pope hath in other countries plaide his vagaries, to the diſturbance of publike vnitie and racking of common wealthes by pillage &amp; extortio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo hath he vexed me with viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t turmoiles &amp; chargeable
<pb facs="tcp:9005:24"/>impoſitions to my no ſmall griefe, and no leſſe detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I can not yet forget the dealing of that gréedie cormorant, and ſweating Bull of <hi>Baſan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A laſt of the Popes prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe here in England.</note> whom I laſtly recited, who in the raigne of king <hi>Henry</hi> the third, ſent ouer his Legate, rentgatherer, or caterpiller, to purloine from mee of euerie Church throughout the Realme a yearely reuenue of foure markes: the which to what ſumme it amounteth I refer to your conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. His letters mandatorie were deliuered into the hands of the Archbiſhops &amp; Biſhops for aſſiſting of the Legate in his collection: enioining them withall to prouide thrée hundred of the beſt benefices, to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied vpon thrée hundred <hi>Italians</hi> at his appointment. Was not this to charge them to rend the fléeces from off their own backes, for the couering of his filthineſſe? The king being certified of the matter calleth a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node of Biſhops, and cauſing conference to be had in their conuocation houſe,
<note place="margin">The king of Englands care for the welfare of his Realme and ſubiects.</note> he thereupon addreſſeth his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the Pope, in his owne name, and in the behalfe of his ſubiects. But when he ſaw his trauell beſtowed this way to be fruſtrate, he imparted the matter to his Lords aſſembled in Parlement, diſcourſing what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences muſt of neceſſitie enſue, if they obeyed the Popes precept: and in moſt earneſt and diſcrete maner he debateth the cauſe ſeuerally with euerie par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Biſhop, willing them to weane their affection from ſtraungers, and not practiſe the vndoing of their natiue countrie for gratifying of the Pope. But fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them peruerſe he mingleth his intreatie with me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces, denouncing openlie againſt them the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the lawes and auncient ſtatutes of his Realme: charging them further vpon their allegeance to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer no money out of the Realme to the beggering of the State. They (as beſt became them) yéelded at the laſt, obedience to their Liege Lorde.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Gregorie</hi> thus defeated of his purpoſe and
<pb facs="tcp:9005:25"/>croſt with a contrarie cue, cleane beſide his expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, began to make batterie with his gunſhot of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, directed to the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> of whoſe inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was beſt perſwaded, with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute it in moſt vehement ſort, that no poſſible furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſhould be omitted for the effectuating thereof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a certaine day preſcribed, wherein the Audit of this ſacred receipte muſt bee giuen vp. The matter was ſo diligentlie trauerſed, what with the kinges Embaſſadors on the one ſide, to appeaſe the Pope; what with the inſatiable couetouſneſſe of the Pope on the otherſide to impoueriſh the Realme, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all importunitie, ſubmiſſion and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable proffers that the king could make, no ſpéeche of reconcilement would be harkened vnto, vntill he had graunted the Pope a tenth of all goods moueable in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> and <hi>Scotland:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The king in his owne Realme ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waighed by the vſurped authoritie of the Pope.</note> and then (to vſe <hi>Matthaeus Pariſienſis</hi> his own words) <hi>Our Lord the Pope being before in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlie inflamed aboue all thinges to ſuppreſſe the hautineſſe of the king, recomforted with theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, was made to conſent.</hi> The which how pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous it became to the ſtate of this Realme can hardly by anie eſtimate be comprehended. For irregular cuſtome hauing once ſet in his foot, would not for many yeares after take the repulſe. So that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath to her ſhame approued the veritie of this ſaying; <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio peperit Diuitias; ſed Filia deuorauit Matrem:</hi> Religion brought forth Riches; but the Daughter ſwalowed vp the Mother, like the Vipers brood. Such gourman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſers as praie vpon Princes, whereas they ought of duetie to pray for them, will be found to haue runne farre into arrerages, when it ſhall be ſaid vnto them, <hi>Giue account of thy ſtewardſhip, for thou maiſt be no longer Stewarde.</hi> Of ſuch it may bee ſaide, as <hi>Alcibiades</hi> ſaid to <hi>Pericles,</hi> when he perceiued him very carefull to make vp his reckonings to the <hi>Athenians;
<pb facs="tcp:9005:25"/>O how much better were it for thee, if thou couldeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe to giue no accounts at all.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The king of <hi>Englands</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>checquer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furniſhed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of ranſoming the Pope.</note> It is not vnknowne howe the treaſure of this realme was of late yeares tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when that ambitious Prelate Cardinall <hi>Woolſey</hi> conueied at one time out of the Kinges Exchecker two hundred and fourtie thouſand poundes ſterling, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuing of Pope <hi>Clement,</hi> whom the Duke of <hi>Bourbon</hi> after the ſacking of <hi>Rome,</hi> drew foorth of the Caſtle of Saint <hi>Angelo,</hi> and detained him priſoner in the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours armie. The which ſummes of monie he conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to furniſh the french King with neceſſaries to make warre vpon the Emperour, who was then in league with King <hi>Henrie</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſpeake of pardons, Peter-pence, with a number ſuch polling &amp; pedling deuiſes of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion wheref the manifeſtation of the Goſpel hath clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſburdened you? What ſhould I declare how licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly he hath preſumed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>troll the mightie kings of <hi>England,</hi> infringing their liberties, abrogating their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, repealing their ſtatutes, and ingrating vpon their prerogatiues? Wherein if hee were at any time gainſaid or ouerthwarted, he then caſt about to depoſe them. As, <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeconde was ſuſpended from his Crowne by the ſpace of foure daies; went barefoote to <hi>Thomas Beckets</hi> Tombe dying the rough ſtones with his blood: and moſt vnkingly deiecting himſelf to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled with the rod, of the Monkes of <hi>Canterburie.</hi> King <hi>Iohn</hi> was miſerably vexed by <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, forced at laſt to reſigne his Crowne with all title of ſouerain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> into <hi>Pandulphus</hi> hand, who detaining it fiue daies, then reſtored it. This infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate King after a troubleſome and litigious raigne was in the ende poiſoned by a traitorous Moonke; as alſo <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi> was by a Dominicane Frier, who miniſtring y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament vnto him, had before dipped the oſte in poiſon. I muſt néedes
<pb facs="tcp:9005:26"/>highly commend the courage of king <hi>Henry</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt,
<note place="margin">The magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity of king <hi>Henrie</hi> the firſt, in with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Hope.</note> who beeing in contention with <hi>Anſelme</hi> about inueſtitures, pleaded the ſufficiencie of his owne authoritie within his proper territories, ſaying; <hi>There is an ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of my kingdome ordained by my Father, that no perſon ſhal ſue anie appeale from vs to the Pope: whoſoeuer will attempt to violate this cuſtome, doeth offend againſt our Maieſtie, and the Crowne of Englande: hee that will ſeeke to deſpoile vs of our Crowne, is an enemie, and a Traitor to our perſon.</hi> And againe, when <hi>Anſelme</hi> would haue had him follow the Popes Letters: <hi>what haue I to doe with the Popes Letters, I will not breake the lawes of my Realme for the pleaſure of anie Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As touching his market-making and whole ſale of ſpirituall promotions to rawe and bankerout chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, it was truely ſaid that the ſtate of Aſſes was much better then of Horſes; becauſe the Horſes were faine to poſt to <hi>Rome</hi> for benefices, but the Aſſes obtained them. Of his ordinarie abſolution for mony without reſpect of crime, he deſcanted pretily that ſaid, Friers were fed fat with mens ſinnes. Of the ſciſmes in his Sea, he ſpake rightly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> being aſked why in their ſuffrages they praied not for Cardinals &amp; Biſhops, that is (quoth he) vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood where we ſay, <hi>Oremus pro ſciſmaticis &amp; haereticis;</hi> let vs praie for ſciſmatikes &amp; heretikes. I omit his beaſtly gaine raked out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinkhole of brothel-houſes. I loth to think vpon his tolerating of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt ſtinking ſin of abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Sodomitrie: in commendation whereof <hi>Iohn Caſus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Beneuentane,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popes Legat to the Venetians wrote a booke. O deteſtable impudencie, to magnifie that in words, yea in writing, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely thought wherof woundeth the heart with horror. Indéed <hi>Sineſius</hi> wrote a pamphlet in praiſe of <hi>Baldnes: Fauorinus</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quartane ague: <hi>Apuleus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aſſe: <hi>Eraſmus</hi> not vnwittily blazed the praiſe of <hi>Follie:</hi> &amp; one of late pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:9005:26"/>out the praiſe of nothing, yet to ſome purpoſe: but what age euer hatched ſuch a forlorne monſter as this? Yet was he a deuout Catholike, a Romiſh Prelate, and one of ſpeciall account with his holineſſe: therefore I mate well thinke like maiſter like man: But roome now, els ſhall we bring all <hi>Rome</hi> on our back: for the Pope ſits in S. <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire forſooth. Why, ſo did the Scribes and Phariſies in <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeate: yet no into the holier men for that. So that I maie iuſtly ſay of him, as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> ſaid to a certain odde <hi>Seriphian,</hi> who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected to <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> that his renowne aroſe more through the glorie of his countrie, then by the merite of his vertues: Not ſo: ſaid <hi>Themiſtocles:</hi> for if I were a <hi>Seriphian</hi> I woulde not liue without honour: and though thou were an <hi>Athenian</hi> thou couldeſt not liue without ſhame. So, if Saint <hi>Peter</hi> were at <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">It is an odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon betwixt S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Pope.</note> he liued not like the Pope: and if the Pope ſit in Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire, yet he liues not like Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> Yet dare his blinde bold bayards make compariſon, and caſt him their gauntlet that will auouch the contrarie. For they affirme his integritie of life to be vnſpotted, and the ſinceritie of his doctrine vncorrupted. They wil ſay Saint <hi>Peter</hi> wrought miracles: I cannot denie it: and to counteruaile that the Pope ſpeakes Oracles: I dare not belieue it: and they cannot proue it. But I iump in opinion with him, who anſwered, when as the Pope vainely vaunted of his heapes of gold, ſaying: I cannot ſay as S. <hi>Peter</hi> did, gold and ſiluer haue I none: No (ſaid the other) nor you cannot doo as S. <hi>Peter</hi> did, cauſe the lame to ariſe and walke. But as <hi>Neanthus</hi> hauing got <hi>Orpheus</hi> harpe went about iangling and iarring ſo long, that wheras he expected the trées ſhould haue dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed after his pipe, he brought the dogs about his eares: ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope hath ſo long boſted of <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſt diſcern his doubling, &amp; he that hath but halfe an eie may find out his groſſe iugling, &amp; legerdemain. Yea, God
<pb facs="tcp:9005:27"/>hath raiſed vp diuers of his owne part, to publiſh his dealings, who if they ſhould all haue held their peace, the verie ſtones would haue cried out for the diſplaying of the ſame. I will not wade any farther in recounting the actions of holy Father Pope, &amp; holy mother Church, beeing matter ſo tedious for the length, and for the beaſtlines ſo loathſome; but will knit it vp with this conceited Paſquine:
<q>
                  <l>Roma quid eſt? amor eſt. qualis? praepoſterus. Vnde hoc?</l>
                  <l>Romamares. Noli dicere plura, ſcio.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And yet behold, your reſtles and retchles deſire lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth and laboureth to inthronize this bloodſucking Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niball, this brocher of quarrelles, this patrone of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, this robber of churches, this controller of Princes, this enemy of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">Both the meanes and the end of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration are matters of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme follie.</note> Neither are the meanes whereby ye would plant him any leſſe peſtilent, then the ende wherfore. Inuaſion of the Spaniard is the meanes; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing of Papiſtrie is the end. It is a common ſaying, He blames <hi>Neptune</hi> without cauſe, that hauing once made ſhipwracke, will to ſea the ſecond time. You haue had alreadie ſome experience of the Spaniardes diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition among your ſelues, and may elſewhere take per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitter notice. So that in this your intent I cannot more aptly compare you then to a foole that laugheth and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſemblance of mirth when he goeth to the ſtocks to be puniſhed for his follie. But if it be a point of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for a man to looke to his owne houſe when he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his neighbours roofe on fire, then firſt learne that point, leaſt in neglecting it ye ouerſée the beſt point in your tables. What the Spaniard hath attempted in the low countries, is better knowne then I am able to report: and what he had attained ere this, may partly be coniectured, if God had not mooued her Maieſties minde, and ſtrengthened her hand to bridle his tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, to ſuccour their diſtreſſes, and ſupport his owne trueth. Conſider what he hath done in the kingdome of
<pb facs="tcp:9005:27"/>
               <hi>Naples</hi> and in the <hi>Indies,</hi> and truſt him accordingly. When <hi>Naples</hi> came to his hands, it had in it ten Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nine chiefe Officers, nineteene Dukes, one &amp; twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Marquiſes, three &amp; thirty Earles, beſides of Barons and Lords a great number. He obtained it by a preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed title of marriage, after it had bene defended a longe time againſt the Emperour by <hi>Francis</hi> the french king: vnder whoſe regiment the people had retained theyr ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed franchiſes &amp; liberties.
<note place="margin">How y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of <hi>Spaine</hi> came to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y the realme of <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </note> But when the french king was taken priſoner at <hi>Pauia,</hi> one condition of his deliuery was, that he ſhould from thence forward with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw his forces out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of <hi>Naples:</hi> by which meanes it came to the king of <hi>Spaines</hi> poſſeſſion. The Spaniardes at their firſt comming ſhewed themſelues moſt pliable in their behauiors, promiſing golden mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, &amp; vowing all ſeruice to the Neapolitanes for the defenſe of their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try &amp; continuance of their fréedomes. And thus by cloked amity they crept into credit: ſo that diuers of the chiefe of them were imployed in the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt fortreſſes, &amp; beſt fenſed caſtles in the country. The king of <hi>Spaine</hi> to curry fauor with them and to rock ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition a ſleepe, appointed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince of <hi>Salerne</hi> their owne countriman to be his Lieutenant. During the while he was ſole gouernour they enioyed all benefits that they had afore time. Not longe after he ſent thither one <hi>Don Pietro</hi> a Spaniard, whom he ioyned in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion with the Prince. This fellow ſought by raiſing falſe reports of the Prince to diſcredit him with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons: and by indirect practiſes to indaunger his life. Which when the Prince ſawe, he willingly ſequeſtred himſelfe departing to his caſtle, &amp; left all affaires to be ordred by <hi>Don Pietro.</hi> The Spaniard not thus contented contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued matter of accuſation againſt the Prince, charging him with treaſon: whereto he refuſed not to make his anſwere. Which when he came to haue done, the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard had ſuborned a villayne pryuily to lurke in the
<pb facs="tcp:9005:28"/>mountaines to haue murthered him with a gunne, who miſſing his body ſtrake him in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leg. The Prince ſéeing himſelfe enuironed with manifeſt perill, tooke his way to <hi>Venice:</hi> vpon whoſe departure the Spaniard immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately proclaimed him traitor. The prince framed his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint to the king, but founde no remedy. Not onely was the offendor releaſed from ſentence of law: but al inborne ſubiects of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme were diſcharged from bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring rule or office whatſoeuer. All Marchants and arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers were prohibited to kéepe any kinde of armour or weapon in their houſes: yea, ſo much as ſworde or dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Only to gentlemen it was permitted to haue their ſwords &amp; targets &amp; none other. If all paiments which al the kings y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raigned before in <hi>Naples</hi> were laid togither, they are not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable to th'extraordinary taxes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath exacted of them.
<note place="margin">The greuous exactions rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon the Neapolitans.</note> Euery fourth or fift yeare they paide ſometime two hundred thouſande, ſometime foure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; ſometime a million of gold. Al ſuch as had lands were called to know by what title they kept the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: if they had not euidence preſently to ſhow, they were defeated, thogh they were able to declare their poſſeſſion of an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or two hundred yeares. Againe, all ſuch, as either themſelues or their anceſtors had born any kinde of ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtracie, were called to account, &amp; notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding they had bene cleared many yeares before by receiuing theyr <hi>quietus eſt:</hi> yet if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quittance were loſt by reaſon of time, they were condemned to repay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole. I might make ſpecial relation of all acciſes, cuſtomes, &amp; exactions, that he impoſeth vpon al manuary trades &amp; mechanicall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties: vpon al co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> may any way grow to the inhabitants: but they woulde require a large treatiſe. But think to what an huge maſſe of mony it amou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth when the Farmar of the butchery and pultry of the city of <hi>Naples</hi> payeth daily thrée hundred ducats: when vit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailers pay fiue ducats for yerely obedience: ſhoomakers one french crowne: filkemakers fiue: when for euery chimney he hath ſixe ſhillings thréepence: of euery ſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet
<pb facs="tcp:9005:28"/>or curtizan thrée ſhillings peny half peny, and of all others in proportion. Euery head of great cattel payeth thrée <hi>Caualluchi</hi> (of the which, fourtéene or fiftéene make a peny) euery head of ſmall payeth two: and (as it is credibly recorded) that taxe in one yeare, onely in two ſhieres <hi>Apulia</hi> &amp; <hi>Calabria</hi> came to foure hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand french crownes ſterling: and there followed the next yeare after, a taxe of ſix hundred thouſand frenche crownes. We vſe to ſay, where nothing is to be had the king looſeth his right. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spaniard though he make his gaine his right, and his will his law: though he haue brought the people to a low ebbe &amp; a miſerable ſtate, yet will he haue what taxes ſoeuer he liſt to leuie, though he rake it out of their bowells, and pull their ſkins ouer their eares for it.</p>
            <p>Theſe are his practiſes in <hi>Naples:</hi>
               <note place="margin">The cruelty of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards in the <hi>Indies.</hi>
               </note> but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> execrable ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies which the Spaniards haue ſhewed on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, as they doo almoſt ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t credit, ſo can they hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be furniſhed with termes effectual to decipher them. They haue diſpeopled in <hi>India</hi> more then ten realmes, greater then al <hi>Spaine, Aragon,</hi> &amp; <hi>Portugall:</hi> which nowe remaine as a wildernes abandoned &amp; deſolate, being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as populous as was poſſible. Within the ſpace of forty yeres, they as in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon butchery ſlaughtered of innocent lambs, aboue twelue millions, men, women, &amp; children. At their firſt arriuall they were intertained w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> performance of al ſeruiceable curteſies, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Indians moſt humbly ſubmitting themſelues vnto them, &amp; after a ſort adoring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as diuine creatures deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded from heauen: but after they were too well acquainted w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> their ſauage cruelties, they fled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hatefull furies broke looſe out of hell.
<note place="margin">The Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards made it a ſport to mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians.</note> The Spaniards cuſtomarily diſported the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in laying of wagers which of them ſhoulde w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one thruſt of a ſword panch or bowell an <hi>Indian</hi> braueſt in the midſt: or w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one blow moſt deliuerly ſtrike off his head: or beſt diſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber him w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one ſtroke. They vſed to mutrher y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords &amp; nobility, by broiling them on gredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons
<pb facs="tcp:9005:29"/>with a ſoft fire vnderneath, that yelling and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing in thoſe lingring torments they might ſo giue vp the ghoſt. Foure or fiue of the Lords on a time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing roſted on this maner, with their pitifull roring and lamentation diſquieted the Captayne (the caytiffe I ſhould ſay) and broke his ſleepe: wherevpon for his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quiet he commaunded them to be ſtrangled:
<note place="margin">This <hi>Peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> wanted but a <hi>Phalaris</hi> to ſerue him of the ſame ſauce.</note> the Ser geant woulde not ſuffer them to die ſo eaſie a death: but himſelfe putting bullets in their mouth to the ende they ſhould not crie, roſted them ſoftly after his deſire. If at any time by due order and formall proceſſe of lawe, a malefactor being a Spaniard were put to death by the <hi>Indians,</hi> the Spaniards ordayned a decree among them ſelues, that for one Spaniard they were to flay an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Indians. A certaine <hi>Indian</hi> Lord flying from out the Ile <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi> into the Ile <hi>Cuba,</hi> was by the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards ſo continually purſued, that at laſt they apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, and burned him with the reſt of his company. When he was bound to the ſtake, a Franciſcan Frier began to common with him touching the knowledge of God &amp; principles of Chriſtian faith. Which thinges al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the noble man had neuer heard of before, yet hee gaue good eare to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Frier who was earneſt to perſwade him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> if he belieued thoſe matters wherein he inſtructed him, he ſhould goe to heauen to inioy euerlaſting happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: otherwiſe, there was no way but to hell with him to indure perpetual torments. The L. ſomewhat paw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing at the matter demaunded of the religious, whether the Spaniardes went. To heauen without queſtion, ſaid the Frier, becauſe they die in the Catholike fayth: the L. hearing him ſay ſo,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Indian</hi> though it bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter to be in hel then to liue with the Spa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niards.</note> anſwered immediately with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further deliberation, that he would not goe to heauen, becauſe he would not come in place where Spa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niards were, nor haue ſociety with a nation ſo cruell. When a certain tyrannicall gouernor entred vpon the firme land, a Lord of the country to gaine his good will and to auoid torture, preſented him with the waight of
<pb facs="tcp:9005:29"/>nine thouſand Ducates. The Spaniardes thinking to wring out of him an ample booty by compulſion, who of his voluntary accord had made ſo large a proffer, layde holde on him, faſtned him to a ſtake, and ſetting him on the earth with his feete ſtretched out, put fire thereto, to make him bring forth more treaſure. The L. ſent to his houſe, and cauſed three thouſand Caſtillans more to be brought and deliuered to them. They not yet ſatiſfied gaue him the torments a freſh: not ceaſing to frie his feete at the fire, till the ſinewes braſt and the marrowe ſpange forth, trilling downe to the ſoles of his feete: ſo that of the ſame cruelty he died.</p>
            <p>Another monſter after he had wrought a moſt bloody maſſacre vpon diuers Lords and other Indians, out of whoſe handes one noble man with his retinew to the number of thirty or forty had eſcaped, &amp; incloſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues within a temple, the Spaniarde following after them, neither waighed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reuerence of the place, nor the innocenci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the perſons, but deuoide of all humanity &amp; compaſſion, ſet fire on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple &amp; ſo burned them. Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the meane while vſed like geſture &amp; behauior, as did <hi>Nero</hi> when he had cauſed <hi>Rome</hi> to be fired, &amp; he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding it ſate ſinging &amp; playing on his harp. This ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant paſſed on to <hi>Mexico</hi> trampling in humane bloode. <hi>Motenzuma</hi> king of <hi>Mexico</hi> being aduertiſed of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſent a thouſand preſents to welcome him,
<note place="margin">Corpora ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnanimo ſatis eſt. &amp;c.</note> &amp; met him at the barres of the citie attended on with an hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable troope of nobles: but that ſame daie by a diueliſh Spaniſh ſuttletie they got the king into their hands &amp; then loded him with bolts &amp; gyues. The Indians thogh they were greatly agréeued at the wrongfull impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their king, yet becauſe he had giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtraight commandement that they ſhould not ſéeke to reuenge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſpite, they indeuored themſelues with pageants, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and ſuch paſtimes, as they could beſt deuiſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort their captiue king, aſſembling as nigh the houſe where their king was as they could. Beſides the floure
<pb facs="tcp:9005:30"/>of theyr nobility gathered together in a place adioyning to the walles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> palace where <hi>Motenſuma</hi> was, vnder ſhow of fained mirth hiding ſad hearts &amp; heauy chéeres. The Spaniard purpoſing to ſtrike a terror into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants bordering &amp; confining thereby, determined to publiſhe a frightfull ſpectacle: and gaue his helhoundes charge that at an appointed houre they ſhould ſet vpon them,
<note place="margin">The <hi>Indians</hi> lamentation for the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les cruelties of the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> at <hi>Mexico</hi>
               </note> and ſiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yong gentlemen being aboue two thouſand, and ſlue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt with an horrible ſlaughter. The Indians are wont in dolefull maner to bewaile &amp; deplore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outragious ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day, eſpecially the deſtruction of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ofſpring of theyr nobility, in whom theyr ioy &amp; glory did princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally conſiſt. This diuell incarnate was accuſtomed when he went to make war on any City or prouince, to carry thither of the <hi>Indians</hi> yoaked together an huge multitude, to fight againſt their neighbors &amp; brethren, &amp; allowing no ſuſtena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ten or twenty thouſand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hee led a long in his army, he licenſed them to eate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Indians</hi> which they could take. So y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he had in his camp an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſhambels of mans fleſh, where before his face they killed &amp; roſted children; they murthred men only to haue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them their hands &amp; their féete which they counted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daintieſt morſells. Another villainy he vſed, which was to ouercharge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſerable people w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cumberſome bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens chaining them togither by the neckes; &amp; when any hapned for lack of meate, or length of iourney, or exceſſe of waight to faint or fall ſick, becauſe he would not ſtay to vnlock the chaine, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpéedier diſpatch he cut off the head from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhoulders, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head tumbled one way, &amp; the body another. Thus many times of thrée or foure thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſhere returned not to their houſes ſixe a liue. The poore wretched creatures, when they wer to go on theſe voiages in this maner, parting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other they wold ſay: In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places where we were wont to ſerue the Chriſtians, howbeit we trauailed ſore, yet at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt wee came home againe to our houſes, our wiues, &amp; our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; but now we go without hope euer to come back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
<pb facs="tcp:9005:30"/>to ſée them. What ſhould I talke of eight hundred <hi>Indian</hi> ſoules partakers of reaſon giuen for one Mare? Or of their forraging with fierce mankinde Maſtifes, hunting after men &amp; women? From the which a ſéely woman ſéeing ſhe coulde not eſcape, hanged her ſelf, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing tied at her foote her yoong babe of a yeare old: but by the time ſhée was dead, the curres came &amp; ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies deuoured the infant. Another hunting abroad after Veniſon, &amp; finding no game met with a woman, whom hee bereft of her tender childe: cut off firſt his armes, then his legs, caſting them to his dogs for liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and laſtly threw the whole carcaſſe among them.</p>
            <p>It is impoſſible for me to vtter in wordes the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciles dealings of the Spaniardes in the <hi>Indies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Non mihi ſi centum Dens or a ſonanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> linguis Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niumque ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pax totumque Helicona de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſet, &amp;c.</note> the gaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remembrance whereof is able to daunt the ſtouteſt courage. So that after this ſhow it is altogither ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous to bring vpon the ſtage the wicked practiſes of the holie Inquiſition, vnles it were to fill vp a roome of impietie if anie bee vacant. Therefore only thus much, they greatly pretend ſupporting of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith, but they wholly intend the multiplying of their priuate commoditie: to whome I may apply the fable of the Lion, who being hurt by the Bull comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all horned beaſts preſently to auoid the forreſt, vpon paine of his diſpleaſurs. Amongſt the reſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> made haſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, was a beaſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> had a bunch of fleſh in his forehead: the For méeting him aſked whether he poſted ſo faſt: he anſwered, good faith I neither iuſtly know, nor greatly care, ſo I were once gone. Why ſo I pray thée? Tuſh, what a queſtion is that? as if thou were ignorant of the late edict y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Liou cauſed to be publiſhed, that no horned beaſt ſhould remain within the wood. I know it well: but that is no reaſon why thou ſhouldeſt either flée or feare: for thine is no horn &amp; therfore it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerns thée not. Marry, that is true: but yet if the Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay it is an horn, in what caſe am I then? So he that comes within the clawes of that holie Court, whatſoeuer his religion be,
<pb facs="tcp:9005:31"/>if his purſe be well repleniſhed, he ſhall either burne for an heretike, or paie well for the ſagots. Whether hée can ſaie <hi>Shibboleth,</hi> or <hi>Sibboleth</hi> it ſkilleth not: they will bear him down he is an <hi>Ephraimite.</hi> Such are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, ſuch are their fruites: fruites farre worſe then the fruites of <hi>Sodome.</hi> For they though bewtifull in ſhew, yet being handled fall to aſhes, only to the delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of him that would crop them: theſe glorious in appearance, but being touched turne to poiſon, euen to the deſtroying of them that credit them. Are ye then ſo fooliſh to looke for Grapes vpon thornes, or Figges vpon thiſtles? Doo ye take pleaſure in the <hi>Sirenes</hi> ſong? or pitie of the <hi>Crocodiles</hi> teares? will ye follow the <hi>Hiae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> voice? or dare ye ſwallow a Spaniſh bait? <hi>Sic notus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes?</hi> Know ye not an Eft from an Eele? Learne to anſwere them as the Fore anſwered the ſicke olde Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when hée intreated him to enter into his denne. Naie, ſaith the Fore:
<q>
                  <l>—Nam me veſtigia terrent:</l>
                  <l>Omnia te aduerſum ſpectantia, nulla retrorſum.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>The tracks and footeſteps that I ſpie</l>
                  <l>make me ſuſpect ſome traine:</l>
                  <l>Sith all looke forward to thy denne,</l>
                  <l>but none looke back againe.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Remember the reward the Sabines beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the damoſell <hi>Tarpeia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A friendly ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat, to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors from pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> when ſhée in lieu of betraying the Citie of <hi>Rome</hi> into their hands, had demanded thoſe things which they wore on their left armes: they gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and after they had compaſſed their purpoſe, they performed their promiſe. But whereas ſhée thought to haue receiued their golden bracelets, ſhée was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed and ſlaine with their ſtéele targates: both which thinges they carried on their left armes. The Spaniardes are perfect in <hi>Gordians</hi> precept, who wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, if thou wouldeſt haue thine enemie flée, to make him a golden bridge to run ouer. The Spaniard know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> readieſt way to win a fort is to batter it with
<pb facs="tcp:9005:31"/>bullets of gold. He knoweth this; he vſeth this: too well he knoweth this to his aduantage; too much hee vſeth this; and too late he hath vſed it to my griefe. It is a ſaying well knowne; <hi>Proditionem amo ſed odi prodito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi> Me thinkes your dealings are liuely deſcribed in the picture of <hi>Furie,</hi> who is painted with a ſword in his hand, and for the impatient deſire of reuenge wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he is inflamed, deſperatly ruſheth vpon a iauelin, ſlayeng himſelfe while he attempteth to annoie his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie: ye are farre more beſotted than that fooliſh fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that was content to forgo one of his eies, conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie his companion might looſe both. But if this that I haue ſaid do not alter your minds, I doubt whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer may be ſaid will be inſufficient. And therefore in reſpect of your obſtinacie I am to wiſh that ye might be dealt withall as the eagle dealeth with hir yoong ones, who tumbleth ſuch out of hir neſt as can not ſtedfaſtly looke againſt the ſunne beames: or that there were ſome deuiſe for the riddance of traitorous papiſts out of the realme, like to that which king <hi>Edgar</hi> inuented for the auoidance of wolues when he bound the Welſhmen to paie their tribute with wolues ſkinnes.</p>
            <p>If haply your maladie be paſt recouerie, I will not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding comfort my ſelfe by repeating the words which <hi>Mardocheus</hi> vſed, in a caſe that threatned as great extremitie. When <hi>Haman</hi> had obtained of king <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> that all the Iewes within his Prouinces ſhould be deſtroied,
<note place="margin">Eſter. 4</note>
               <note place="margin">An example of ſinguler comfort to all faithfull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes.</note> &amp; had got the proſcription co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed vnder the kinges ſeale manuell, <hi>Mardocheus</hi> being a Iewe, &amp; vncle to quéene <hi>Eſter,</hi> certified her by the kings Eunuches of <hi>Hamans</hi> procéedings, and ſent her the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie of the commiſſion, charging her to become petitioner and frame ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the king for her people. When <hi>Eſter</hi> heard the wordes of <hi>Mardocheus</hi> ſhe commanded the Eunuche to tell him, that the law was ſo: whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhould come into the kings preſence vncalled, muſt die, vnleſſe the king of his grace held forth his ſcepter
<pb facs="tcp:9005:32"/>vnto him: <hi>Now,</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>I haue not beene called to the king theſe thirtie daies,</hi> which when <hi>Mardocheus</hi> vnderſtood, he returned her this anſwere: <hi>Thinke not with thy ſelfe that thou ſhalt eſcape in the kinges houſe more then all the Iewes. For if thou holdeſt thy peace at this time, comfort &amp; deliuerance ſhall appeare to the Iewes out of another place, but thou &amp; thy fathers houſe ſhall periſh. And who knoweth whether thou art come to the kingdom for ſuch a time?</hi> So though you being animated through the Popes abſolution, and in hope of I know not what lordlie preferments haue agréed among your ſelues to make away with ſuch as ſhall not be found to haue an <hi>Auemaria</hi> ſticking betwixt their téeth, or an <hi>Agnus Dei</hi> couched in their boſome: yet becauſe your rage is raiſed againſt the Lord, &amp; your tumult aſcended into his ears, I truſt he wil doe to you &amp; to your confederats as he did to proud <hi>Senacherih,</hi> put an hooke into your noſtrils and a bridle into your iawes. For as it was prophecied of <hi>Troie,</hi> that it ſhould not be ſubdued ſo long as the <hi>Palla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium,</hi> which fell down fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wals therof, remained within it: ſo I am aſſured that <hi>England</hi> ſhall haue reſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all her enimies ſo long as Gods holy word ſhalbe ſincerely preached &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly followed.
<note place="margin">Our ſins the meanes to draw Gods plagues vpon vs.</note> For there is nothing that can withdraw his bleſſings from vs, or draw his puniſhments vpon vs, but our ſtiffnecked and vncircumciſed harts, which neither haue thankfuly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued his truth, nor yéelded obedience vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. And were it not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> there is a zealous <hi>Moſes</hi> among vs, whoſe praiers appeare before the Lord as incenſe, &amp; the lifting vp of whoſe hands is as an euening ſacrifice:
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> were there not a iuſt <hi>Loth</hi> who day by day vexeth his ſoul in ſeeing our vnlawfull deedes, &amp; by continuall interceſſion ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the heat of Gods wrath: I feare me your vngodly purpoſes had ere this preuailed, &amp; his heauy indignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſumed vs.
<note place="margin">Exod. 17.</note> But whenſoeuer <hi>Moſes</hi> hands ſhal begin to ware wearie: when <hi>Loth</hi> ſhall once depart out of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9005:32"/>then I feare leſt God lay the raines on your neck, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yoke on ours: leſt he grant vnto you power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoile, &amp; allott vnto vs ſodaine deſtruction: then I feare leaſt as the floud was in the ſpring of the yeare, and the burning of <hi>Sodome</hi> at the riſing of the Sunne: So I feare (I ſay) leaſt Gods comming vnto vs be in the winter of our faith, and the ſummer of our pride: and leaſt hee thruſt the ſickle of his vengeance into the full harueſt of our iniquities. Let vs therefore learne to loue him as a father: and let vs not forget to feare him as a Lord. Let vs not deſpiſe the riches of hys bountifulnes patience, and long ſufferance: knowing that by the ſame he allureth and leadeth vs on to repentaunce: the differring whereof is moſt daungerous, for ſo muche as it is to be giuen of hys mercie, &amp; not commanded at our pleaſure: <hi>Nam qui promittit poenitenti venia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, non promittit peccanti poenitentiam:</hi> He y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promiſeth pardon to him that repentes, doth not promiſe repentance to him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offends.</p>
            <p>As for you let this ſuffiſe, that there was a curſſe denounced againſt him, that ſhoulde build vp <hi>Iericho</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: that <hi>Achan,</hi> with his familie, his cattell, his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementes, and all that hee had, was ſtoned and burnt in the vallie of <hi>Achor</hi> becauſe he had taken a Babiloniſh garment, certaine ſhikels of ſiluer, and a wedge of gold, being excommunicate things, and hid them in his tent: &amp; dare ye then ſhrine ſuch abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in your harts? Surely I greatly doubt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> as the Lord plagued al <hi>Iſrael</hi> till they had puniſhed <hi>Achan,</hi> ſo hee will not leaue to ſcourge vs till we haue rooted out all of <hi>Achans</hi> brood. The example of <hi>Tarquin</hi> in cutiing off the toppes of the poppies was moſte happilie imitated to the glorie of God and benefite of the Realme: for by that meanes I truſt the ſtalkes will ſoone wither away.
<note place="margin">The Queene of Scots the roote of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes.</note> But while the roote remained whole, it nouriſhed a great number of noiſome and ſuperfluous branches. Our malcontent Romaniſts were ſo affectionately deuoted to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triuing of her contentment, as <hi>Aeolus</hi> was deſirous
<pb facs="tcp:9005:33"/>to gratifie <hi>Iuno</hi> when hee ſayd: <hi>Tuus, O Regina, quid optes</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>Explorare labor: me iuſſa capeſſere fas eſt.</l>
                  <l>To thinke the thing thou faine wouldſt haue,</l>
                  <l>pertaines (O Queene) to thee:</l>
                  <l>But to performe what ere thou craue,</l>
                  <l>that dutie longs to me.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Your villanies before theyr late diſcouerie, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in your owne conceits wellnigh to haue attained the higheſt ſtep of theyr perfection: ſo that if <hi>Sinon</hi> could haue brought the horſe within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates of <hi>Troy,</hi> he ſhould then haue giuen the watchword to the <hi>Grecian</hi> Fleete houering aloofe at <hi>Tenedos.</hi> Then would it haue bene to late to haue wiſhed for <hi>Hector,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Politus</hi> ſhould haue bene ſlaine at the altar and ſanctuarie; when <hi>Caſſandra</hi> ſhould haue bene rauiſhed in the temple; and <hi>Priamus</hi> murthered in his own Pallace. O vnſpeakeable grief! all theſe valefull calamities to haue ſprung from one <hi>Helena?</hi> How much better had it bene that that <hi>Helena</hi> had neuer bene borne? or being borne, a thouſand tymes better, ſhe ſhould haue bene throwne into the middeſt of the ſea with a milſtone about her necke, then to haue bin the ſubiect for ſo many tragedies. When <hi>Iabin</hi> king of <hi>Canaan</hi> ſought to oppreſſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> by the handes of <hi>Siſera</hi> his captaine;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udic. 4.</note> the Lord raiſed vp <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi> to ouerthrow his power. But the mother of <hi>Siſera</hi> making iuſt reckoning of victorie, looked out at the windowe, and cried through the latteſſe, why is his Chariot ſo long a comming? why tarrie the wheels of his Chariot? haue they not gotten, &amp; nowe they deuide the ſpoyle? &amp;c. The mother, ſiſter, coſin, or friend of <hi>Siſera,</hi> or howe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhe were allied vnto him, looked, &amp; long ſhe looked; but in ſtead of <hi>Siſera,</hi> contrarie to her hope, ſhe ſaw <hi>Iehu</hi> come to doe iuſtice. The Lord looked alſo downe from heauen, hee ſaw your deuiſes: hee liked them not, but laughed becauſe hee perceiued your day was comming: yea, hee looked long: at laſt he ſawe iuſtice done, and it pleaſed him well. For my part I will euer pray, that I
<pb facs="tcp:9005:33"/>may rather beare the burthen of <hi>Deborahs</hi> ſong, then the burthen of <hi>Phineas</hi> wiues ſorrow. The ſong of the one was; <hi>So let all thine enemies periſh O Lord:
<note place="margin">Sic <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. bethae mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lunt.</note> but they that loue him ſhalbe as the ſunne when he riſeth in his might.</hi> The ſorrow of the other was; <hi>The glorie is departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Iſrael;</hi> for the Ark of the Lord is taken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe a liue dogge is more to be doubted then a dead Lion, I wiſh that all theyr lurking holes may be narrowly ſearched, and they ferretted out of theyr Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niburrowes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 101.</note> where priuily they lay wayt for innocent bloud. I pray God, her Maieſtie may perfilly learn <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> ſong,
<note place="margin">Traytors preſume upon her M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>s mercie.</note> who ſaid he would ſing vnto the Lord of <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and iudgement.</hi> Her clemencie hath bene moſte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly abuſed; the muſick had almoſt bene mard, and all like to be brought into an vnpleaſant diſcord, while ſhe harped ſo long vpon one ſtring. The ſeruauntes of <hi>Benhadad</hi> king of <hi>Syria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reg. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> what iniuries ſoeuer they had wrought <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet when they were fallen into the lapſe they comforted themſelues with theſe wordes: Behold, we haue heard ſaie that the kinges of the houſe of <hi>Iſraell</hi> are merciful kings; let vs therefore put ſackcloth about our loynes, &amp; ropes about our heades, and go to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> it may be that he will ſaue our liues. They ſtood vpon what may be, and what he wil do: not vpon what muſt be, &amp; what he ought to doe; &amp; thus they made mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy the groundwork of their miſchiefe. But the king of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was reproued by the Prophet, who tolde him; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt let goe out of thy handes a man whome I appointed to die, thy life ſhal goe for his life &amp; thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for his people. No leſſe are thoſe runnagate ruffians to be regarded, who practiſe to ſteale away the harts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, crying out with the black mouth of <hi>
                  <hi>Rabſakeh:</hi> What ſay ye vnto me, we truſt in the Lord our God?
<note place="margin">Eſay. 36.</note> Is not that he whoſe high places, &amp; whoſe altars <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias</hi> took down? &amp; am I come vp without the Lord to this land? therfore let not <hi>Ezechias</hi> deceiue you, for he ſhall not be able to deliuer you.</hi> And as <hi>Artabanus</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9005:34"/>king of the Perſians anſwered the letters of <hi>Alexander</hi> emperor of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaying: <hi>In ſtead of paper J aſsigne him the field, a lance for the pen, bloud for inke, &amp; wounds for words:</hi> So theſe companions for diſputations bring diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for reaſons treaſons, arguing <hi>ab vtili,</hi> and not <hi>ab honeſto:</hi> concluding neither <hi>honeſtum</hi> nor <hi>vtile:</hi> arming their religion with atheiſme: and ſupporting theyr faith by faithleſſe trecheries. Yet when they are cut ſhort by iuſtice,
<note place="margin">Papiſtes make treaſon the truit of conſcience.</note> they wouldimpudently face out the matter, that they die for their conſcience, whereas (God knoweth) their conſcience was dead long before. But we may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere their great maiſter, as king <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt did, when the Pope ſent to him commanding him to releaſe the Biſhop of <hi>Beauuois</hi> and his Archdeacon, whome hee called his ſonnes, being taken by Earle <hi>Iohn</hi> the kinges brother in the field, and by the king co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to priſon, he ſent to the Pope theyr complete armour, with this meſſage,
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 37.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide an tunica filij tui ſit an non:</hi> ſée whether this be thy ſonnes coate, or not. Let the pope looke whether his Ieſuites iett in the garments of godly Churchmen, or rather of roiſting vagabondes: let him ſaie if theſe be the doings of men that deale vpon zealous conſcience, or rather vpon traiterous intent. Theſe are they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by their whiſpering tales would put men in fear where there is no cauſe of feare: giuing falſe fires, and ſtriking vp hote alarmes, when there is neither ſhot nor ſouldier nigh ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,
<note place="margin">Papiſtes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to amaze men with cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe feare.</note> thinking to make men afraid of ſkarcrowes, of their own ſhadows, or rather of nothing at al. Theſe are they that conſtrue euerie accident that befalles to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their purpoſe, ſpeaking as they would fayne haue it. Theſe are they that vſe wicked conſultation in holie places, prophaning temples by their lewd confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and making the houſe of prayer a den of theeues. In a Church-yard in <hi>Paris</hi> ſhortly after the bloudie maſſacre ſprong vp a Palme tree: which the Papiſtes ſtraight interpreted to be a ſigne that the Proteſtants were fullie vanquiſhed, and the lott of victorie falne
<pb facs="tcp:9005:34"/>to theyr part. But it was indeede a true token, and <hi>Time</hi> which is <hi>Truthes</hi> mother, hath prooued it ſo to be, that howſoeuer they practiſed by violence to extirpate true profeſſors, yet maugre their malice, his ſeruants ſhould floriſh like the Palme trée, and that from their blood as from the aſhes of the Phenix ſhould reuiue a glorious of ſpring. For the blood of Martyrs is the ſéede of the Church. And therefore as <hi>Alexander</hi> the great couragiouſly anſwered, when his ſouldiors would haue diſſwaded him from going vnto <hi>India</hi> becauſe the image of <hi>Orpheus</hi> ſwet: what? (quoth <hi>Alexander</hi>) doth <hi>Orpheus</hi> ſweat? then I know we ſhall make worke for the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets: ſo we, though, not <hi>Orpheus</hi> image, but <hi>Orpheus</hi> Ape, <hi>Neanthus</hi> whom I touched before; though (I ſay) the Pope ſweat and ſweare, and take on as one of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors did for his pie: yet we know that in maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Gods truth, &amp; obeying our ſoueraigne we ſhall doe a worke acceptable to him: but they and you, which doe the contrarie, will make worke daungerous to your ſoules, damageable to your countrie, &amp; onely profitable for the hangman. I wiſh you better, &amp; I would I might hope better of you; and when I ſée you begin to amend, then ſhall you ſée me leaue off to miſtruſt. But though faintnes now inforce me to ſhut vp my complaint, yet vntill that time, neither can I be fréed from feare, nor you cleared from ſuſpicion.</p>
            <p>O Louing God, and moſt mercifull Father,
<note place="margin">A prayer for the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her maieſtie and continuance of the goſpel.</note> who hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt in thy hand the harts of all Princes, &amp; turneſt them which way ſtandeth beſt with thy diuine plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, we beſéech thée ſo to order the thoughts of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant our dread ſoueraigne, and ſo to diſpoſe all her acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that as a faithfull handmaide, ſhe may ſtudie to pleaſe thée, and as a carefull nurſe ſéeke to cheriſh thy Church. And foraſmuch as thy glorie is chiefly ſhewed by bringing to paſſe thy will through weake meanes &amp; féeble inſtruments, aſſiſt her we pray thée with thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, that being weake in her ſelfe ſhe may be ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:9005:35"/>by thy arme, to confound all ſuch as ſhall with <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lofernes</hi> aſſault thy people. And as thou haſt hertofore of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes redéemed her out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of the lion, ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend her ſtill, that neither open force nor ſecret villanie at anie time preuaile againſt her. And ſéeing theſmall graine of thy Goſpell which by her hand thou haſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſown amongſt vs in the field of thy Church, hath béene ſo watered with the heauenly dew of thy bleſſing, that the birdes come now &amp; build in the branches there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: and the ſlender vine that thou broughteſt out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, and plantedſt in this land, hath through thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe taken ſuch roote, that the mountaines are now co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with the ſhadow of it, &amp; the boughes therof ſpread abroad like the goodly Cedar trées: we beſéech thée to watch ouer it, that neither the Caterpiller which lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in corners conſume it, nor the wilde Boare out of the wood deſtroy it, but that being nouriſhed by thée, it may grow vp before thée, &amp; bring forth fruite vnto thée. Remember not our former iniquities, but let thy tender mercies preuent our imminent miſeries. And as in the daies of <hi>Ioſua</hi> thou didſt ſtay the ſunne in the firmament vntil thy people had cleane vanquiſhed their &amp; thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies: ſo now maintaine the throne of thine annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that her daies may be as the daies of heauen for brightnes, and as that day of <hi>Ioſua</hi> for continuance, that ſhe may wéed out the aduerſaries of thy truth, that ſo the worke which thou haſt mercifully begun, may be proſperouſly perfited by her. Let it neuer be tolde in <hi>Gath</hi> that the glorie of <hi>Iacob</hi> is darkened; let it neuer be publiſhed in <hi>Aſhkelon</hi> that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcepter of <hi>Iudah</hi> is falne, leſt the daughters of the Philiſtines reioice, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed begin to triumph. But let all the world know that thou careſt for thy people and vpholdeſt thine heritage. As for thine enimies they ſhall be as the ſmoke that vaniſheth in the wind; as the waxe that melteth at the fire; and as the duſt that is ſcattered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tempeſt. They ſhall periſh, yea they ſhall all periſh at the rebuke of thy countenance.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9005:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
